<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the saving grace of God by ... David Clarkson ...</title>
            <author>Clarkson, David, 1622-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12535</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12388641</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12388641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 657:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the saving grace of God by ... David Clarkson ...</title>
                  <author>Clarkson, David, 1622-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 151, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Astwood for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: prelim. p. [15] and p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:1"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE Saving Grace OF GOD.</p>
            <p>By the late Reverend and Learned <hi>DAVID CLARKSON,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Aſtwood,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>three Crowns,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE very Title-page, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the <hi>Subject,</hi> and the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe,</hi> leaves little need of a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what <hi>Subject</hi> can be ſuppoſed more inviting than this of <hi>the Grace of God?</hi> repreſented to ſuch as <hi>were loſt,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning their <hi>Salvation?</hi> If we were the Inhabitants of ſome other World, never loſt, or in which Sin, and Vindictive Juſtice had no place; 'twere a grateful Contemplation to us, if from thence, we had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to view the Methods of Grace for
<pb facs="tcp:60922:3"/> the ſaving of miſerable periſhing Creatures in ſuch a World is this. As the kindneſs, and benignity of the unfal'n <hi>Angels</hi> makes them <hi>ſtoop down</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, and pry, with <hi>earneſt deſire</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 12.</note>, and no doubt high pleaſure, to obſerve what was doing to this purpoſe in this wretched World of ours.</p>
            <p>But who can conſider <hi>himſelf</hi> as loſt, and not apprehend the name of <hi>ſaving grace</hi> to carry with it a pleaſant, joyfull ſound? It too plainly argues a ſtrange complication of <hi>ſtupidity,</hi> and <hi>lightneſs of mind,</hi> when to any, who are <hi>themſelves of</hi> that <hi>loſt race,</hi> the Grace of God, by which only they can be ſaved, is unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and without reliſh. And it is not leſs ſtrange if they can expect to be ſaved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
            <p>There are ſo many <hi>ſenſible Miſeries</hi> continually urging Mankind, that if they be compared with what obtains in the common belief of the moſt (of whatſoever Religion,)
<pb facs="tcp:60922:3"/> and whereof few profeſs any doubt, that one would wonder all ſhould not be much taken up in meditating ſome way of eſcape, and how they may be ſaved out of ſuch a Gulf as this. For, ſetting aſide the inward evils that infeſt mens minds, (which carry moſt of Sting and Pungency in them, to thoſe of an awakened <hi>mental ſenſe)</hi> 'tis obvious to their <hi>duller outward ſenſes,</hi> that they are encompaſſed, and often ſeiz'd with innumerable Calamities, Sickneſſes, Pains, Violences from one another, and other diſaſters, from which they cannot be certain to be ſafe one moment, and that they are all mortal, and after a little time muſt certainly dy. The moſt profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to believe they have about them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what immortal, and that this World will at length have an end. Divers <hi>Pagans</hi> have agreed with <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it will end by Fire, an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Conflagration, and of an after Felicity to be had ſomewhere elſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:4"/>
            <p>Now what <hi>Power of Nature</hi> can they think of, that ſhould ſave them out of ſo common a Ruine? Or what is left them to think of beſides, unleſs they will yield themſelves to periſh without remedy (which the Nature of man abhorrs from) but of <hi>being ſaved by Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that have any Notion of God, cannot think <hi>Grace</hi> unworthy of him. Some of the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Faith, that thought it unſuitable to the Nature of God to be toucht with <hi>Anger</hi> (and who might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think our Infelicities to befall us of courſe, without being any effects of divine diſpleaſure) yet were leſs averſe to think he might be toucht with <hi>Grace,</hi> (as <note n="*" place="margin">De Irâ Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> takes notice,) and ſo left themſelves room for the apprehenſion, that our Felicity ſhould be owing to the Benignity and Favour of God. But what thoughts of Him can be more unworthy, or leſs agreeing with themſelves, than, while he is acknowledg'd to be a
<pb facs="tcp:60922:4"/> 
               <hi>Mind,</hi> a <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>firſt, eternal Mind,</hi> and the <hi>Father of Spirits,</hi> to ſuppoſe he ſhould be leſs kind, benign, and gracious to our Minds, and Spirits, than to our baſer Fleſh? Or that they who expect from his favour a ſtate of future freedom from bodily pains, diſeaſes, and death, ſhould not expect from it much more a Felicity ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Nobler part? and ſeek thence what is of ſo apparent neceſſity, before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, to prepare and form their Minds and ſpirits for ſuch a Felicity?</p>
            <p>And one would think, that as they who are better inſtructed in the Affairs of Gods Government over men, and that know how to aſcribe to him a juſt diſpleaſure, and anger for their common Apoſtacy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from him, that ſhall be no way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming, but moſt agreeable to an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely perfect Being; ſhould be moſt apt to approve, and admire the Methods, which the Grace of God hath pitcht upon, for expiating the guilt of Sin by a Redeemer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:60922:5"/> ſo they ſhould not be unapt to apprehend the Neceſſity of gracious Operations upon the ſpirits of men, to deliver them from ſuch diſtempers and diſaffections, as are plainly inconſiſtent with their final Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Bleſſedneſs; and give them ſuch diſpoſitions as are requiſite thereto.</p>
            <p>Can any thing be more ſuitable to the Grace of God, than, when he hath found out a way, wherein he might, upon terms not injurious to the dignity of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, pardon their ſins, he ſhould alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly apply himſelf to them, cure the blindneſs, carnality, and averſion of their Minds, incline, and inable them to know, truſt, love, obey, and converſe with him, without which an Atonement, and pardon would avail them nothing, and in which of themſelves they can effect nothing?</p>
            <p>'Tis eaſie to frame <hi>abſtract Diſcourſes,</hi> and <hi>general Ideas</hi> of what might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by thoſe <hi>noble Powers,</hi> a mans own <hi>Underſtanding,</hi> and <hi>Will:</hi> but what
<pb facs="tcp:60922:5"/> can actually be effected, in particular, and circumſtantiated caſes, againſt the ſtream of ſenſual Inclination, either <hi>to the inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of intenſe thoughts,</hi> or by <hi>think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> they perhaps are moſt apt to pronounce confidently, who have leaſt tryed.</p>
            <p>Nor is any thing more congruous to the <hi>notion of Grace,</hi> than that it be <hi>at liberty</hi> herein. <hi>Unfree Grace</hi> were to every mans underſtanding a plain contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. Neither can any inconvenient or ill Conſequence follow upon its being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended moſt ſovereignly free. Or any thing that is not moſt ſuitable <hi>to God,</hi> and <hi>to us.</hi> It naturally follows that He be not neglected, that He be ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſought unto, that we abſolutely, and with great <hi>reverence,</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> ſurrender, reſign, and commit our ſelves to Him. Which how majeſtick, auguſt, great, and God-like is it, <hi>on his part!</hi> how correſpondent to his very Nature! Whereupon we are told, <hi>(Pſalm 147. 11.)
<pb facs="tcp:60922:6"/> The Lord taketh pleaſure in them that fear him; in thoſe that hope in his mercy.</hi> And how ſuitable is it to the <hi>condition of wretched and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent creatures</hi> that are periſhing, and cannot ſave themſelves! And to ſuch one would think no ſubject ſhould be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable than this of the ſaving Grace of God: Nor therefore a Diſcourſe upon it unacceptable.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially from <hi>ſuch an Authour,</hi> who tho his great Humility, and remoteneſs from all Oſtentation of himſelf, did as much vail him, as was poſſible to him; yet his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Worth could not be hid, and indeed the leſs, by how much the more he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd it. His clear and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Mind, his excellent Learning, his reaſoning argumentative Skill, his ſolid, moſt diſcerning Judgment, his indefatigable Induſtry, his large Knowledge, and great Moderation in the matters of our unhappy Eccleſiaſtical differences, his calm diſpaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:60922:6"/> Temper, his pleaſant and moſt ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Converſation did carry ſo great a luſtre with them, as that, notwithſtanding his moſt beloved Retiredneſs, they could not, in his Circumſtances, but make him be much known, and much eſteem'd, and lov'd by all that had the happineſs to know him; and make the loſs of him be much lamented. But he was by the things that made his continuance ſo deſirable in this World, the fitter for a better, and more ſuitable World. He liv'd here as one that was more a-kin to that other World than this; and who had no other buſineſs here, but to help in making this better. From <hi>ſuch an hand</hi> one may reaſonably expect a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> very highly valuable <hi>upon ſuch a Subject.</hi> Which I do with ſo great confidence, that, thô I have not as yet (wanting Opportunity) throughly perus'd it, I make no doubt to invite ſuch to the reading of it, as appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the value of the <hi>Grace of God,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:60922:7"/> and their <hi>own Salvation,</hi> earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that, as their Satisfaction herein may be, in its completion, alike early; ſo it may be equally great with that, which is with much aſſurance expected by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>One very deſirous any way to promote the common Salvation, John Howe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Enſuing DISCOURSE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THat Salvation is wholly and only from</hi> Grace, <hi>proved,</hi> Pag. 1, 2.</item>
               <item>Grace <hi>free in reſpect of 1. Conſtraint, 2. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 3. Motive,</hi> p. 3, 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That Salvation is by Grace, demonſtrated from God, from Man,</hi> p. 5, 6.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>From Man, in ſeveral particulars,</hi> 7, 8, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>From God, demonſtrated in ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</hi> p. 17, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Uſe. <hi>Thoſe condemned who will have us ſaved by</hi> Free-will, <hi>and not by</hi> Free-Grace, 27.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Doctrine of</hi> Free-will, <hi>diſplayed, in four particulars: 1. What Grace the Patrons of</hi> Free-will <hi>do own, and count ſufficient. 2. What they aſcribe to</hi> Free-will. 3. <hi>What is the Tendency of their Principles. 4. What they Object againſt the Doctrine of</hi> Free-Grace, p. 28.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:60922:8"/>
               <item>1. <hi>What</hi> Grace <hi>by them is counted ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> p. 28, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>What they aſcribe to</hi> Free-will, p. 33.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>The Import and dangerous Tendency of the Doctrine of</hi> Free-will, <hi>in twenty particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> p. 39, 40, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Objections againſt the Doctrine of</hi> Grace, <hi>anſwered, and Prejudices removed,</hi> p. 112.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Some Practical Inferences from the Doctrine of</hi> Free-Grace, p. 147.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <head>Books written and publiſhed by the Author of this enſuing Treatiſe, and ſold by <hi>Tho. Farkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NO Evidence for <hi>Dioceſan Churches,</hi> nor any Biſhops without the Choice or Conſent of the People, in the Primitive Times. Or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Allegations out of <hi>Antiquity</hi> for ſuch Churches, and againſt Popular Elections of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: In a late Volume, Intituled, <hi>The unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of Separation:</hi> Shewing that they do not ſerve the Deſign for which they are produced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dioceſan Churches</hi> not yet diſcovered in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times. Or a Defence of the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Stillingfleets</hi> Allegations out of Antiquity for ſuch Churches. Againſt the Exceptions offered in the Preface to a late Treatiſe called <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60922:8"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF Free-Grace.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EPHES. II. 8.</bibl>
               <q>By Grace ye are ſaved.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1-51" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle, the great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerter of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>Verſe,</hi> compares the Church to <hi>a Temple:</hi> And it is his deſign in this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to ſhew the Influence Grace hath to the raiſing of this Building. He undertakes to prove, that the whole Structure of Salvation is to be attributed alone to Grace.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60922:9"/>
               <p>The Foundation was laid from Eternity by Grace in Election, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 4, 5. The poliſhing and diſpoſing of each particular Stone in the Building, by Juſtification and Sanctification, were all acts of Grace; <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 7. &amp; 2. 5. &amp; 4. 13, 14. And it is Grace that lays on the Top-ſtone in Glory; <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. 6. So that we may honour this Temple with the ſame Acclamations, which they uſed to theirs, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4. 7. and cry <hi>Grace, grace,</hi> unto it. The ſumm of the whole Diſcourſe is propounded in the Text, <hi>By Grace ye are ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will not divide what God from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity has joined together, <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> But from them intirely taken, offer you this</p>
               <q>Obſervation, <hi>Salvation is wholly and only to be attributed to Grace.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>We need go no further for divine Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to this Truth, than theſe two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Election, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 4, 5. Redemption, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. Vocation, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Juſtification, <hi>Chap. 2. ver.</hi> 3, 4. Sanctification, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Glorification, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. What he ſpeaks of the whole here, he affirms of every part thereof in thoſe places. The whole and all the parcels are of Grace.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60922:9"/>
               <p>For Explication. By <hi>Salvation,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand both the Decree of God, by which the Elect were ordained to Salvation, and the Execution of that Decree, begun here, and conſummated in glory.</p>
               <p>That we may know what Grace means, take notice of three words, uſed promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in Scripture, which yet admit of ſome diſtinction; the knowledge whereof will lead us to the diſtinct knowledge of this term. Theſe are <hi>Love, Mercy, Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To <hi>Love,</hi> is <hi>velle bonum,</hi> to will the Happineſs of the Object loved. It is not in God ſuch an affection as in us, though in effect it proves <hi>affectus unionis,</hi> and brings God and his People together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercy</hi> does <hi>velle bonum miſeris.</hi> So it adds a Limitation to the Object, which Love leaves indefinite. It is for thoſe that are miſerable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grace</hi> does <hi>velle bonum liberè.</hi> So this limits not the Object, as the former, but qualifies the Act. It acts freely.</p>
               <p>So that Mercy is Love to thoſe that are miſerable. Grace is Love in him that is unobliged. Unobliged, I ſay, either by Neceſſity, Merit, or Motive. Grace then, in God, is nothing but <hi>free Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Free in reſpect of <hi>Conſtraint;</hi> when there is no neceſſity he ſhould fix his Love
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60922:10"/> upon this Object at all, or upon this rather than another. This is <hi>ſpontaneum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Free in reſpect of <hi>Merit;</hi> when there is nothing in the Object that deſerves Love, either abſolutely or comparatively, this is <hi>gratuitum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Free in reſpect of <hi>Motive;</hi> when there is nothing in the Object to move this Affection to pitch upon it at all, or upon it rather than another. This is <hi>liberum,</hi> tho' it expreſs it not fully.</p>
               <p>In all theſe reſpects, the Grace of God in beſtowing Salvation upon any of the Sons of men, is free Love.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There's no Neceſſity God ſhould ſave men. He is a moſt free Agent, whoſe liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is inconſiſtent with every degree of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity <hi>ab extra.</hi> It was in his choice either to have created no man, or to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned all men, or to have ſaved thoſe who are now condemned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is nothing in Man that can me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Salvation: for there is no good thing in him that he can call his own. All is of Gift; and the beſt thing in man bears no proportion to Salvation: but where there is Merit, there muſt be both Propriety and Proportion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is nothing in Man can move God to ſave him. If any thing, his Miſery;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60922:10"/> but this is no Motive abſolutely, becauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is wilfull. Man willingly involved himſelf in it, and is unwilling to be delivered from it upon the terms propounded in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. Nor can it be a Motive comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſave one man rather than another, becauſe all are by nature equally miſerable.</p>
               <p>So then Salvation is by Grace, becauſe it is a gift of free Love to ſuch in whom there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can be nothing to inforce it, nothing to deſerve it, nor any thing to move him to beſtow it.</p>
               <p>The Demonſtrations are drawn from <hi>God,</hi> from <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>Man.</hi> The <hi>Impotency, Deformity, Enmity</hi> of man againſt God, makes it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that Salvation muſt be wholly, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Impotency.</hi> What a poor deſpicable creature is Man! the beſt of men! What a wonder the great God ſhould think of ſaving him! His riſe was from the Earth. He is but at beſt Duſt and Aſhes, a poor piece of Clay. He dwells in houſes of Clay. His Foundation is in the duſt, and is cruſhed by the Moth, <hi>Job</hi> 4. 19. A ſtately thing ſure which the very Moth can cruſh, and crumble into his firſt principle, Duſt.</p>
               <p>The moſt potent victorious King, that ever <hi>Iſrael</hi> had, puts a Worm amongſt his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60922:11"/> titles, <hi>Pſ. 22. 6. I am a Worm.</hi> The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man in the Eaſt derives his Pedigree no higher; <hi>I have ſaid to corruption, thou art my Father, and to the Worm thou art my Mother and my Siſter,</hi> Job 17. 14. And if the greateſt men on earth, who beſt underſtood themſelves, were no greater in their own account; what do we think men are in Gods account? The numerous poſterity of <hi>Jacob</hi> have no greater Title, <hi>Iſa. 41. 14. Fear not, worm Jacob:</hi> and if that vaſt multitude, which was like the Stars of the Heavens, and the Sands on the Sea-ſhore, which cannot be numbred, be but as one Worm in his eye; what do we think is one Man?</p>
               <p>But we are too high yet. Men in the account of God, compared with him, are not ſo much as Worms. Abſolutely, in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are more; but compared with him not ſo much, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 22. It is he <hi>that ſitteth upon the Circle of the Earth, and the Inhabitants thereof are as Graſs-hoppers;</hi> this is ſomething leſs than Worms; yet leſs in his eye, than theſe in ours.</p>
               <p>But we yet go lower. Worms and Graſs-hoppers, tho' moſt deſpicable, are yet animate Beings; and the ſoul of the leaſt Creature, in <hi>Auguſtins</hi> account, is more excellent than the Body of the Sun. This is too high yet;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60922:11"/> What then are men in Gods eſteem? ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 15. The <hi>Nations are as the drop of a Bucket, and are accounted as the ſmall duſt of the Ballance: behold he takes up the Iſles as a very little thing.</hi> What? all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth as one drop? As an Atom? What proportion then do ye think we bear to this drop, to this Atom, who are but as drops and Atoms in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all the Nations of the Earth.</p>
               <p>Sure now we are low enough. Our thoughts can ſcarce go lower. I, but ſtay, we are not in Gods account thus much. A drop, an Atom is ſomething, tho a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thing. But <hi>Ver. 17. All Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him are as nothing.</hi> Alas, where are we then, ſo near the low condition of Non-entity? Yes, and lower too; for it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>and they are accounted to him leſs than nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See then what Man is in Gods account, as leſs than that which is leſs than nothing. And can you imagine any thing in this Nothing, man, that ſhould oblige the great God to ſave him? O, ſure it is Grace, free Love; and ſuch as may aſtoniſh Heaven and Earth; that the great God, who meaſures the Seas in the hollow of his Hand, who ſpans the Heavens, and weighs the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, ſhould condeſcend to do thus much
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60922:12"/> for any of theſe poor deſpicable nothings: ſhould contrive their Salvation from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and ſend his Son, the Son of his Love, of his delight, to procure it with his Blood, and then admit them to an eternal injoyment of himſelf in Glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Deformity</hi> of man as he is ſinful. We ſhewed before, man was Nothing, leſs than nothing, in the ſight of God. Now we will ſhew, he is worſe than nothing; even a deformed nothing, or rather no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Deformity.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, by Creation he was a beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Creature, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lded after the Image of the firſt Beauty, bearing the ſuperſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God. He was then as a bright Morning Star, when he firſt appeared in the World. But he forthwith fell from his primitive ſtation, the Orb of Innocency: He fell from thence into the Puddle of ſin, into <hi>thick mire and clay,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 2. And being drenched in ſin, he became more deformed and abominable in the eye of God, than that which is moſt loathſom to us. The vail of Light and Holineſs, wherewith he was Beautified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing torn off the Soul, Sin beſmeared it with ugly filthineſs and pollution. The divine Light and Holineſs, which ſhined in his Soul, is vaniſhed; and Darkneſs and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60922:12"/> Deformity has ſeized on him, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread him. Holineſs was the moral Form of the Soul; but now ſin gives it morally both its being and denomination. So that, what may be ſaid of ſin in the abſtract, as that it is Deformity, Pollution, Filthineſs, may be ſaid of man in the concrete, he is deformed, filthy, polluted. We have cauſe to complain of this woful change, in the words, of the Prophet, with a little vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, <hi>Iſa. 3. 24. Inſtead of a ſweet ſmell,</hi> there is <hi>a ſtink, inſtead of well-ſet hair bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and Deformity inſtead of Beauty.</p>
               <p>Sin has left neither <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Souls of ſinners, neither Proportion nor good Complexion. The Fall put all out of joynt, and left the Soul blind, lame, crooked, diſeaſed, nay dead in ſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are the familiar Epithets which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gives our ſinful ſtate.</p>
               <p>The Viſage of the Soul is loathſomly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted. Nor has Sin brought upon it ſimple Deformity alone; but, which is worſe, Uncleanneſs, ſuch as is compared to that of a <hi>removed Woman, Ezek.</hi> 36. 17. Nay the beſt thing that is in it, or proceeds from it, is but as a <hi>menſtruous rag, Iſa.</hi> 54.</p>
               <p>I, but thô this be noiſom and unpleaſing, yet there's no danger, no Infection in it. O but ſin is a contagious Pollution, 'tis like a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60922:13"/> Plague-fore in the heart, an infectious Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy; it will diffuſe its malignity like the poyſon of Aſps.</p>
               <p>I, but if a man be viſited with the Plague or Leproſy, he ſeems rather an object of compaſſion, than deteſtation; rather to be pitied than loathed. Go yet one ſtep further.</p>
               <p>Sin is not only contagious, but a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom noiſom Filthineſs. The Holy Ghoſt compares it to the ſtench of an open Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, to the Vomit of a Dog, to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted matter of a putrified Ulcer. Such is the temper of a Soul by ſin.</p>
               <p>I'll go no further. It may be the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe is offenſive; how much more to ſee, ſmell, or touch them. Yet a ſinful man is more ugly in the Eye, more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the Noſtrils, more loathſom to the Lord, than any of theſe can be to the quickeſt or moſt delicate of our Senſes.</p>
               <p>Alas, wretched Man! how juſtly maiſt thou or I ſpeak, what <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> uſes in complement to <hi>David, 2 Sam. 9. 8. What is thy ſervant, that thou ſhouldſt look on ſuch a dead Dog as I am?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can any Soul expect, that ſuch a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as this ſhould be the Object of any ones Love, much leſs of Gods? How hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs may mans Salvation ſeem, if we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60922:13"/> look on him in this ſtate! What! is the eternal Love of God, the precious Blood of Chriſt, for ſuch a Wretch as this! Is there any thing in him, in us, to merit, to move Love? Who would not rather think, every ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould with indignation be kickt out of the preſence of ſo holy a God? Sure if there be any hopes, it muſt be from Grace, free Love, and ſuch as could no where be entertained but in the breaſt of infinite Goodneſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Enmity</hi> of ſinners againſt God, this makes it evident beyond all exception. The Impotency and Deformity of man, in the ſtate of ſin, ſhews there is nothing lovely in him; but if there were not, yet if he had any love for God, this love, without any other conſideration, might be ſome inducement to move the Lord to love him; and ſo his love might ſeem leſs free, as having ſome motive from without.</p>
               <p>But the caſe is otherwiſe. As there is nothing Lovely in him, ſo neither is there any Love to God; nay there is a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Hatred and Enmity.</p>
               <p>The Wiſdom of the Fleſh, the very beſt thing in man, <hi>is Enmity to God, Rom.</hi> 8. 7. And this Enmity is manifeſted in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting the Will of God, and running croſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60922:14"/> to his Commands: for if this be our <hi>love to God,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>that we keep his Commands, 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 3. then this is Hatred of God, that we will not keep them.</p>
               <p>And this Diſobedience of a Sinner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from his Hatred of the God that commands, and not only of that which is commanded, yea rather from that than this. For what Sinner is there, who does not believe, that what the Law commnds is Juſt in it ſelf and good for us?</p>
               <p>So that the Enmity reaches God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Who is the Lord,</hi> ſays the ſinner in his heart, <hi>that I ſhould obey him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, Sinners revolt from God, and conſpire with his greateſt Enemy, joyn in confederacy with Satan. They, (as thoſe in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 15.) have made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Hell; and with Death are they at agreement. They give up their <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as Weapons of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> to fight againſt God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 19. It is the condition of all, by nature. Every Sinner, before the Lord conquer him by his Grace, is at open enmity with God, and does in effect bid defiance to the Almighty. The acts of his life are acts of Hoſtility againſt God. Nor is it a defenſive war only, that would be more excuſeable; but the deſign
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60922:14"/> is, not to ſecure himſelf only, but to put down God, and diveſt him of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty. This is the voice of their Hearts and Lives, We will not have this God to rule over us. Sin, where it reigns, does as much as is in its power to depoſe the Soveraign Lord of the World. It denies in effect that he is God: For that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies his eſſential Perfections and Attributes, does deny him to be God. He that gives up himſelf to ſin, denies in a manner all his divine Excellencies, his Goodneſs, Wiſdom, Power, Juſtice, Mercy, Immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 21. He would not go on in ſin, if he did not ſay in his heart that he is not the Chief Good; becauſe ſin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives him of this Good, cuts him off from the Injoyment of it: or elſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not that it will deprive him of the chief Good, and ſo denies his Truth, who has affirmed and declared it; and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving him herein makes him a Liar.</p>
               <p>He durſt not ſin, but that he thinks God is not preſent to ſee him; and if ſo, he denies his Immenſity. Or if he ſee him, he thinks he cannot puniſh him; and ſo denies his Power. Or if he be able, yet he thinks he will not puniſh him; and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies his Juſtice. He would not turn aſide to other ways than he preſcribes, but that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60922:15"/> he thinks he either cannot direct him in the beſt way, and ſo denies his Wiſdom; or that he will not direct him to the beſt, and ſo denies his Mercy. And thus much we might ſhew of the other Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, how it tends to deface them all.</p>
               <p>Lo here the horrid Enmity of Sin and Sinners againſt God. They deny he is God; call him, conſtructively and in effect, a finite, a weak, a fooliſh, a falſe, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and unmercifull thing.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, Sinners cannot do what they ſay and wiſh in their hearts. They have not Power to undeifie God, or to deprive him of his Divine Perfections; but this does not leſſen nor excuſe their Enmity againſt him: For it is true in evil, as well as in good, Where there is a willing mind, it is accounted as if it were done.</p>
               <p>O the horrid nature of Sin! Be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, O Heavens, and be ye horribly afraid at this Prodigious Enmity, which is in the Hearts of Sinners againſt God. Why is thy wrath reſtrained? O Lord; Why does not thy Indignation break forth, and deſtroy all Sinners from off the face of the Earth? Nay, why was not Heaven and Earth annihilated at the firſt appearance of ſuch horrid Treaſon, of ſuch deſperate Enmity?</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60922:15"/>
               <p>But we have not yet diſcovered the height of this Enmity. What is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that a Sinner ſhould thus ſet himſelf againſt God? It may be, he deſpairs of Salvation, while the Almighty rules; and therefore the deſire of his own Happineſs may be the cauſe of this oppoſition; and ſo it will not be pure Enmity, but ſome Principle of ſelf-love, that may make him ſo deſperate.</p>
               <p>It is no ſuch matter; it is not Salvation that he cares for. He ſets himſelf againſt God; not out of any reſpect to ſecure his own well-being. For whom would he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance into the place of God? 'Tis the great enemy of his Salvation, Satan, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 4. 'Tis he, who by the conſent of Sinners is the <hi>God of this world;</hi> 'tis he they would have to rule in and over them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2. They are Children of obedience to him, but of diſobedience to God, and will be ſo, tho' they periſh for it.</p>
               <p>Here then is the height of the Sinners Enmity againſt God. They had rather pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Eternally under the Soveraignty of Satan, than be happy in ſubjection to the Scepter of God. Nay, ſinners would perſiſt in the height of this Enmity, and therefore reject all motions of Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tho' the Lord condeſcend to beſeech
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60922:16"/> them, with all moving arguments, to <hi>be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 20. They deſpiſe Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and the means that tend to it. They manifeſted it, by crucifying the Lord of Life, when he came on purpoſe into the world to bring Salvation. <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>this is the Heir, Mat.</hi> 21. 38. We cannot reach the Father, he is too far above us; but we have a fair occaſion to ſhew how well we wiſh him. This is the Heir, here is his Son, his only Son, the Son of his Love and Delight, <hi>come let us kill him:</hi> and ſo they did; and ſo would other Sinners do, if they were in the ſame circumſtances with thoſe that did it. And there are thoſe, who <hi>Crucifie again</hi> the Lord of Life. And what do we leſs in venturing upon ways of ſin? ſince this is it which firſt crucified him. This is the deſperate diſpoſition of all Sinners in the ſtate of nature. We had ſo continued to Eternity, if the power of Grace had not broke in upon us, and drawn us to terms of Reconciliation.</p>
               <p>And this being our State and temper naturally, can you think there was any thing in us, that could have moved the Lord to ſave us? What? can Hatred, ſuch deſperate Enmity, ſuch prodigious Malice againſt the Lord, move him to love us?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60922:16"/> O, if free Grace had not moved it ſelf, we had perſiſted in our oppoſition againſt the Lord; and had been eternally miſerable, as thoſe deſerve to be, who are found fighters againſt God, and open Enemies to him.</p>
               <p>There are other Demonſtrations, that Salvation is of Grace only, which may be drawn from God himſelf; the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Allſufficiency, Soveraignty.</p>
               <p>(1.) The <hi>Allſufficiency</hi> and independency of God. He ſtood in no need at all of man, either for Happineſs or Glory, the leaſt degree of either. He had been eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally as happy, as glorious, if man had never been, or been ever miſerable.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of <hi>Happineſs.</hi> He was perfectly, infinitely happy without us. He did not expect, he could not have the leaſt Degree of it from us. All de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, all Fulneſs of it was in himſelf, before we had a being. The Divine Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding was infinitely pleaſed and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Contemplation of himſelf, the firſt Truth. The divine Will took in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite contentment and complacency in the injoyment of himſelf, the chief Good. The Object here was infinite and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Excellencies; and the Acts were infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely perfect; and the Iſſue thereof muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60922:17"/> needs be infinite Happineſs, both formal and objective. Chriſt, the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> of the Father, thus expreſſeth it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22. 30. Here are the mutual delights of the Father and the Son; thoſe injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which hold forth the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Happineſs, before any creature had being. The Son was the Fathers <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> daily,</hi> every moment, without the leaſt intermiſſion; <hi>and rejoyced,</hi> the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>was laughing before his face.</hi> Thoſe happy ſouls, who are already ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the glorious Preſence, may gueſs, tho not comprehend, what happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there is in thoſe delights: we are in the dark, and can neither expreſs nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how much it is; but tho we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive how great that Happineſs is, we may eaſily apprehend, that it cannot be made greater by any creature.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Happineſs muſt ariſe from Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſome good, or the injoyment of it. Now all Goodneſs in Perfection, is included in the divine Being; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good is in the creature, it is but an imperfect participation of that Primitive Goodneſs, or rather but a dim reſemblance of it. And ſhall we think that there can be any addition to his Happineſs from that which is ſo imperfectly without him,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60922:17"/> when all Excellencies are perfectly, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, infinitely in himſelf? Shall the Ocean of Bleſſedneſs ſeek an increaſe from that which is leſs than a Drop? Or the Sun of Glory borrow luſtre from a Glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm, a dim Spark? Or the Univerſe of all Happineſs greaten it ſelf by a Point, a Mote? No, the Lord was Bleſſed for ever, before man was in being; and he had been Bleſſed for ever, if man had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been. And if nothing had moved the Lord to ſave him, but a deſign to add to his own Happineſs, none of the Children of men had ever known Salvation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of <hi>Glory.</hi> The Lord does not depend upon man more for Glory, than Happineſs. He had been as Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if we had continued in the State of Non-entity, or if we had Periſhed in our Sin, and ſunk into Miſery. It's true, we ſay the Lord glorifies his Mercy in our Salvation; but this is ſuch a Glory as he might have wanted, and yet have been no leſs Glorious. To clear this a little. The Glory of God is Eſſential or Relative. Gods Eſſential Glory is thoſe infinitely glorious Perfections and Excellencies which meet in the Divine Eſſence. This is that Glory, which no mortal eye ever ſaw, or can ſee. When <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to ſee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60922:18"/> his Glory, the Lord ſays to him, <hi>Thou canſt not ſee my face and live,</hi> Exod. 33. 18, 20. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace is the Seat of Beauty, where all the lines of Perfection do concenter, where all the rays of Glory are united. Theſe we can no more behold in his face, than a lump of Snow can ſuſtain the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vigor of the Sun-beams at noon day.</p>
               <p>When the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> had ſeen the Glory of <hi>Solomon,</hi> it's ſaid <hi>there was no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in her,</hi> 1 King. 10. 5. The Soul, or Spirit in her (as in others) has a ſtrong inclination to unite with that which it apprehends to be moſt good; and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomething tranſcendently better with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, than in the Body, ſeemed willing for that time to leave the Body, that it might enjoy and cloſe with what was more excellent. If the Lord ſhould unvail himſelf, and let us have a clear ſight of his glorious Excellencies, as they ſhine in himſelf; the Soul would leave the Body, the Union between them would be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; the ſpirit would be wrapt away with ſuch a ſight, and leave the Body dead. This may be the reaſon of what the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes; No man can ſee my face,</hi> i. e. my Eſſential Glory, <hi>and live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, the <hi>Eſſential Glory</hi> of God is God himſelf, and therefore both Infinite
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60922:18"/> and Eternal. It is Infinite as he is, and to that which is Infinite nothing can be added, it can no way be greater than it is already. It is Eternal too, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any thing was created, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no way dependant on the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. By which it is manifeſt, that eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Glory is not at all increaſed by working mans Salvation</p>
               <p>For Relative Glory, that indeed depends on the Creatures. But the Lord had been as glorious in himſelf, if this Glory had never been, as will appear from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it. The eſſential Attributes of God are his divine Perfections, abſolutely exiſting, without reſpect or relation to the Creatures. Relative Attributes are thoſe eſſential Perfections, as manifeſted to the Creatures, or rather the Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of them. If then Eſſential Glory be the luſtre of thoſe eſſential Attributes, as ſhining in the divine Eſſence, which we ſhewed before, it muſt follow, that Relative Glory is that which reſults from the Manifeſtation of thoſe Perfections to the Creatures. For example, Relative Mercy is the Manifeſtation of eſſential Goodneſs in the Salvation of the Elect; and Relative Juſtice is the Manifeſtation of eſſential Righteouſneſs or Juſtice in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60922:19"/> the Condemnation of the Reprobate.</p>
               <p>Now God had been as glorious in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he had never made known his Mercy or Juſtice to the World, if there had been no World, no Creatures made, to manifeſt theſe to, if there had been no Men or Angels to take notice of them. For, is the Sun made more ſplendid or beautiful by our beholding of it? No, it would be as glorious, if no Eye ever ſaw it. Did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> eating Manna add any ſweetneſs to that pleaſant food? no ſure, it had been as ſweet in it ſelf, if no Palate had ever taſted it. Even ſo the Lord had been as powerful, if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver created the World; no leſs merciful in himſelf, if he had never ſaved any, if there had been none to ſave; no leſs righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, if there had been none to condemn, if he had never condemned any.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this may ſeem ſtrange, and ſome may ſtick at it, let me add a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it. The Manifeſtation of his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to the World is a free Act, a tranſient Act. It is a certain rule in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, <hi>Quicquid Deus operatur ad extra liberè fit;</hi> every Act of God terminated on the Creatures, is a free Act. A free Act is that which may be done or not done. So that it was in the choice of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60922:19"/> the Divine Will (before it had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it ſelf) to manifeſt Mercy, or not to ſhew it; to ſave man, or not to ſave him, to make him, or not. But if Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did add any thing to the Glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of God, our Salvation had been a neceſſary, and not a free Act; becauſe without it the Lord had wanted ſome degree of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo had not been moſt glorious, moſt perfectly ſo, and conſequently not himſelf.</p>
               <p>Hence it is evident, that the Lord did not ſtand in need of our Salvation, to make him more glorious any way. He was infinitely glorious from Eternity; but theſe Manifeſtations of himſelf are in time, therefore can add nothing to his Glory, which was infinite before all time. The reaſon why he revealed his Mercy in ſaving man, was not becauſe this was needful to make himſelf more glorious. We muſt, as Chriſt ſhewed us, find the reaſon of it in his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Will, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 25, 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; this was the reaſon of it, <hi>Thy good pleaſure.</hi> And to this the Apoſtle leads us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 5, 9.</p>
               <p>'Tis true alſo, we are ſaid to glorifie God by our Services, by the Acts and Exerciſes of Holineſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 23. and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60922:20"/> 
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 8. But how is this to be under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtood? even as he is ſaid to glorifie him ſelf, when he manifeſts to us that he is glorious. So we are ſaid to glorifie him, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n we acknowledge that he is Glorious, when we give a teſtimony to his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perfections by word or deed. But neither his Manifeſtation, nor our Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, does add to his Glory. He ſhews it, we take notice of it, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe imports any addition to it. Hence <hi>Pſal. 16. 2. My goodneſs extendeth not to thee.</hi> If our Apprehenſions of God were as high as their Object; if our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to him were more than that of the Angels; if all our Prayers and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were Raptures, and all our Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances ſerued up to the higheſt degree of Perfection that a created being is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of: yet were we in this reſpect <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servants;</hi> the Lord upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count would have no advantage by us: for as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſays to <hi>Job,</hi> Ch. 22. 2, 3. <hi>Can a man be profitable unto God, as he that is wiſe may be profitable unto himſelf? Is it any pleaſure to the Almighty, that thou art righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous?</hi> &amp;c. No, the Lord may glorifie us, but he gains no glory by us, that is any advantage to him. He ſtands in no need of us to glorifie him; he had been as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60922:20"/> if we had periſhed, or if we had been nothing. Therefore what Motive can there be in or from us, to oblige him to ſave us?</p>
               <p>(2.) The <hi>Soveraignity</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> of God over his Creatures. As in reſpect of his Alſufficiency, he ſtands in no need of us; ſo in reſpect of his Soveraignty he ows us nothing; he is no way ingaged to us, or obliged by us: but may do what he will with us, either to ſave or not to ſave us. So it ſtands with us clearly, if we conſider his Dominion over us, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedence to his Purpoſe and Promiſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For he might have been ſatisfied in the <hi>ſole injoyment</hi> of his bleſſed ſelf, and never have vouchſafed a Being, much leſs Salvation and Glory, to any Creature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or if he would manifeſt himſelf to the Creatures, he might have formed more <hi>excellent Creatures,</hi> and more fit to be the Objects of his great and tranſcendent Love: for he did not act as a natural Agent <hi>ad ultimum ſui poſſe,</hi> to the utmoſt of all his Power.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or if the Divine Will would deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it ſelf to give a Being to thoſe very Creatures that are now exiſtent; yet there was no neceſſity that he ſhould <hi>ſave any</hi> of them. He might have anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60922:21"/> them, without any ſhew of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes: <hi>For who can ſay unto</hi> the King of Kings, <hi>What doſt thou?</hi> Dan. 4. 35. might he not do with his own what he will?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Or if he would manifeſt his Love and Goodneſs in the Salvation of any that he had Created; yet who would not think all the <hi>Angels</hi> (thoſe ſometimes glorious Creatures) more capable of it, than any of the Children of men?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Or if unworthy Man muſt be the Subject of it; yet why <hi>ſo many</hi> men? He might have made fewer Veſſels of Mercy, than are now formed by it, to be for eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> filled with it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Or if he would pitch upon ſo many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet why <hi>upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe</hi> who are now ſet apar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for Salvation, rather than thoſe who are <hi>paſt by?</hi> Why are theſe choſen, and the other left? Why are theſe Veſſels of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour rather than the reſt, when all were of the <hi>ſame Clay,</hi> formed by the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 25. There's no Reaſon ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be given, but his <hi>good pleaſure,</hi> his mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grace. And, O what beams of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Grace do break forth from this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration! What! muſt Men be choſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from all other Creatures to be the Object<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods <hi>peculiar Love?</hi> Will the Lord
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60922:21"/> vouchſafe the eternal Enjoyment of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to none but Men alone of all lapſed Creatures? <hi>Lord! what is Man that thou art mindfull of him, or the Son of Man that thou viſiteſt him!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And how exceedingly does this endear Free Grace, that any of us ſhould be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the reſt of periſhing Sinners; that we ſhould be Veſſels of Mercy, when others are Veſſels of Wrath! Lord, what are we, or what are our Fathers? <hi>Why haſt thou revealed thy ſelf to us, and not to the World? Even ſo, Lord, becauſe it pleaſed thee?</hi> No other Reaſon can be aſſigned, but meer Grace. There needs no more, to demonſtrate that Salvation is to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to Grace only.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This condemns their Doctrine, who will have us ſaved rather by <hi>Free-Will,</hi> than by <hi>Grace;</hi> which will have the Text inverted, and read thus: <hi>By Free-will are ye ſaved, not by Grace, but of your ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This has too many Patrons, and thoſe of greateſt Name and Ability amongſt the Oppoſers of Truth. It's the capital Errour of the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> the Foundation of their other Opinions that concern Grace, and with which they all ſtand or fall.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60922:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60922:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60922:23"/> The <hi>Socinians,</hi> and the worſt among the Papiſts, the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> joyn with them, all following <hi>Pelagius,</hi> condemned by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church as the Enemy of the Grace of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>That we may the better underſtand them, and what in them is to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and avoided, let us ſee, (1.) What <hi>Grace they own</hi> and count <hi>ſufficient:</hi> for ſomething they muſt own under this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who will not plainly renounce the Goſpel. (2.) What they <hi>aſcribe to Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.</hi> (3.) What is the <hi>Tendency of their Principles.</hi> (4.) What they <hi>object</hi> againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Free-Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. For the firſt. They count no Grace neceſſary to bring a Sinner into a <hi>ſaving State,</hi> and continue him in it; but that which they call <hi>Morall Grace</hi> or <hi>Swaſion.</hi> This conſiſts in a preſenting of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Will, with Motives and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to embrace it. Or thus, in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of our Duty, with rational Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to move him to yield to it, leaving us to do as we pleaſe. For Example, To turn from ſin to God, and to Believe in Chriſt, are Duties propounded in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; the advantage of yielding hereto, and the danger of refuſing, is there decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60922:23"/> and ſo it is left to the Sinners choice, whether he will comply or no.</p>
               <p>This is all the Grace which the Lord affords to ſave us. It amounts to no more than a moral Excitement, or a rational Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal. This Propoſal is made with ſome light, tending to excite Affection. If it were altogether in the dark, it would be in effect no Propoſal. Whether this Light be natural, or ſupernatural, they are not agreed. Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and thoſe moſt followed, would have the Light of natural Reaſon ſufficient. Others would rather have it counted a Light from the Spirit. But all agree, that it is no ſpecial Illumination, but a common Light, vouchſafed to all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel; and ſo ſuch as thoſe have, who live and dye in the groſs Darkneſs of Ignorance and Wickedneſs, they muſt not by their Principles deny to Heathens. And thoſe, who will have it called the Light of the Spirit, count it as weak and powerleſs as natural Light, <hi>i. e.</hi> of no more power and efficacy to determine or ſway the Will, than the Light of Reaſon; no, nor ſo much as ſome Dictates of Reaſon are commonly thought to have. The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is ſo little (if there be any) as to the thing it ſelf, that thoſe who call it the Light of the Spirit, ſeem but to give
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60922:24"/> it that Name and Title, to decline the Odium of aſcribing nothing at all to the Spirit of Grace. However a common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, with ſuch light, made in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel unto Sinners, is all the Grace which they count needful.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They deny <hi>eternal Grace, i. e.</hi> all Free Mercy in God to any particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from Eternity. According to them, he had no Mercy, no purpoſe of it for any, but what he was obliged to by the foreſight of the good uſe of Free-will. This is no Free Mercy, and ſo no Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They deny all <hi>habitual Grace,</hi> which is not of our ſelves. They will have no ſuch thing wrought in us by the Spirit of Holineſs. All gracious Qualities or Principles, planted in the Heart by the Spirit, they reject under the notion of infuſed habits.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They deny <hi>actual Grace, i. e.</hi> any operation of the Spirit to determine the Will. All gracious influences whatever that will or can certainly incline it to act, or incline it any more to act than not to act. Grace, with them, only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to the Will, and leaves the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to it ſelf; it muſt be left indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to act, or not to act, as it likes.</p>
               <p>No other Grace, than this of propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60922:24"/> none, habitual or actual, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for any Perſon in the eternal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God, or purchaſed for any by the Blood of Chriſt, or adminiſtred to any by the Spirit of Grace. It is enough that it be propounded to the Will to turn to God, and Arguments offered to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſuch as the Goſpel contains, and are managed in the Miniſtry of it. So that all the Grace, which they count neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is no ſpecial, ſufficient Grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is no <hi>ſpecial,</hi> but only common Grace, afforded equally to thoſe that are damned, as to any that are ſaved. No other Grace, than that which ſuffers the far greateſt part of thoſe who partake of it to periſh eternally. That Grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with any man may be damned, as ſoon as ſaved. If any be ſaved in their way, it is without ſpecial Grace. It is ten to one, for any Grace the Lord vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes to Sinners, they will never be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not <hi>ſufficient Grace,</hi> unleſs Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has Power enough for Saving Acts, without the leaſt acceſs of Strength from Grace: for their Grace gives not the leaſt degree of Strength to the Will; but only rouſes its native Power: as <hi>Dalilahs</hi> voice gave <hi>Sampſon</hi> no more ſtrength, when ſhe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60922:25"/> ſaid, <hi>The Philiſtins are upon thee,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excited him to uſe the ſtrength he had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When they will have this ſwaſive Grace to be ſufficient, they commend not Grace at all, but magnifie the Power of Nature, as being great indeed, when it needs ſo little help for Acts of the higheſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and importance. If any be ſaved in their way, it muſt be without any Grace ſufficient to Salvation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not <hi>effectual Grace.</hi> This is plain by the former. There can be no pretence that that will be effectual which is not ſufficient. But ſuppoſe it were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, (as they without ground would have it accounted) yet it is not of it ſelf effectual. The Efficacy of it, by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is not from its own Nature and Vertue, nor from the Spirit of Grace, but from the Will of Man. If he will, it is efficacious; if he will not, it is of no Effect. So that, if it ſhould prove Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to ſave any; yet that is to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to Free Will, and not to Grace; to that which makes it Effectual, when other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would be of no effect.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, it is not <hi>ſaving Grace,</hi> tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it in any of their Senſes. As Saving Grace is peculiar to the ſaved, ſo it is far from being ſaving. In this reſpect it is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60922:25"/> no more ſaving than damning, if ſo much, ſince the moſt incomparably that have it are damned.</p>
               <p>Or if we take <hi>ſaving Grace</hi> for that which is ſufficient for Salvation, it is not ſaving, unleſs there be a Power in mans degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Nature to ſave it ſelf; Power enough in the worſt for ſaving acts, ſuch as needs nothing but exciting.</p>
               <p>Or if we take it for that which is Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to Salvation, it has no ſuch Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy from it ſelf or from God; it is only from the Will of man that it is effectual to Salvation, if ever it prove ſo. So that in their way, either there is no Grace at all that is ſaving, or none that is ſaving at a better rate than the Will of man can make it ſo, when it has no ſaving vertue of it ſelf, or from God.</p>
               <p>There needs no other Arguments againſt this Doctrine, no Artifice to ingage us againſt it, but a true and plain diſcovery of it. If we be ſaved by Grace, this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine tends to lead us out of the way of Salvation.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Let us ſee what they <hi>aſcribe to Free-will.</hi> And that in general is a Power to be willing or unwilling, as to any Motion that is made, any Object that is offered
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60922:26"/> to it. It has a Power of it ſelf, and by its own natural Conſtitution, either to chooſe or refuſe, either to imbrace or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject whatever Object is propounded, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be propounded. The Will, they ſay, is never determined <hi>ad unum,</hi> never ſo ſet upon one thing good or bad, but that by rational inducement, <hi>i. e.</hi> by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Arguments, it may be led to the contrary; and never ſo moved by ſuch inducements, but that it may reject the motion. Never ſo ſet upon Sin, but that by ſwaſive Propoſals it may be moved to leave, not only the Acts, but the State of Sin: nor ever ſo moved by that, or any thing elſe, but that it may repell the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and quite ſtifle it.</p>
               <p>We may view it more diſtinctly in theſe two branches.</p>
               <p>(1.) A Power <hi>to chooſe whatever good</hi> is offered. They will have it able of it ſelf to imbrace any good Object of what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſoever; not only natural or moral but what is ſupernatural, of the higheſt Nature and Quality; and the imbracing of it ſaving, ſuch as will paſs a man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſaving State. It has a Power to repent of ſin, to believe in Chriſt, to turn to God, to love, fear and delight in him.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60922:26"/> Not only a capacity, but an active Power for theſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Only theſe things muſt be propounded to it with ſome clearneſs and earneſtneſs, as the Goſpel propounds them to all under its Miniſtry. And that ſuch a Propoſal is required ſignifies no inabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Will it ſelf for theſe great things: for the moſt ſufficient Faculty imaginable cannot act upon an object that it diſcovers not; and the Faculty of greateſt Power may, in ſome caſes, need exciting. And ſo it is requiſite the will have Light to diſcover its Object, and ſome Arguments to commend it, at leaſt when the Soul is under the diſadvantage of rooted prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or habitual and inveterate wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>However, all the help they think need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Will, is ſo far from denying its Power and Sufficiency for thoſe great concerns of Salvation; that it ſuppoſes the Will to have it in and of it ſelf, if ſaving things be but repreſented to it as neceſſary and worthy of its choice and embraces.</p>
               <p>(2.) A Power <hi>to refuſe any Object,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be offered, with what advantage ſoever it be propounded by the Spirit of God, or the Miniſtry of man. For the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60922:27"/> they make eſſential to the Will, conſiſts, they ſay, in an indifferency, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to chooſe or refuſe, either to act or not to act. And it muſt be left indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in all caſes; ſo that nothing in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Earth can determine it, but it ſelf. God himſelf they ſay cannot without fail determine it to the choice of this or the other without deſtroying it. <hi>Voluntas ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis ad actus ſuos motione irreſiſtibili de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminari non poteſt ne ab ipſo Deo quidem. (Syn. Dor.</hi> 212.) He cannot<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Ames</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. <hi>p. 129.</hi>
                  </note> incline the will irreſiſtably, he cannot by any Divine Motion of unwilling make it willing. Whatever Power he does or can put forth for this purpoſe, the Will may and can reſiſt it and render it of no effect. If the Lord do deſire and intend to Convert a Sinner, and do what can be done by the Power of his Grace in order thereto; yet the Will may hinder him. Take it in their own words, <hi>A man may hinder his own regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, when God has a mind to have him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, and it is his will to regenerate him,</hi> Coll. Hag. 282. <hi>Corvinus</hi> (the moſt ſubtile and cautious of their writers) ſays expreſly, <hi>Poſitis omnibus ad agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Hickm. <hi>p. 33.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>requiſitis,</hi> &amp;c. when all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60922:27"/> the Operations of Grace in order to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion are paſt upon the Will; yet it is ſtill in the free power of the Will to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert or not to convert it ſelf. So that, when God has done his utmoſt to bring a Sinner into a ſaving State; yet it is in the power of the Will to defeat and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. In plain terms, when God has done what he can, the Will may do what it liſt. They will have the Will to be ſo free, as that it can be under no neceſſity of any ſort, not only ſuch as is natural, or compulſive, or abſolute, which is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but ſuch as is only reſpective<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that in reference to God himſelf. So that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f it be needfull in reſpect of the Decree and Purpoſe of God, or in reſpect of his Will and Deſire, or in reſpect of his Word and Ingagement, or in reſpect of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and Intention, that the Will ſhould move this way and not the other; yet it may incline and determin it ſelf the other way; and ſo may act counter to God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe his Concerns, defeat him in them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, and carry it againſt him. The Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe, the Promiſe, the Providence, the Grace of God, the Undertaking of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Operations of the Spirit, may be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rated unavoidably by mans Will. So great
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60922:28"/> a Power they give it. The Lord ſhall not have his Will, nor make good his Word, nor make his Grace prevalent, nor accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his greateſt Deſigns, if mans Will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply not; and it is never under any neceſſity to comply, but may always reſiſt, when the Lord has done what he can to bring it to a complyance. This is the true Viſage of their Doctrine, if you will ſee it plain and naked. There needs no ill Language to render it ugly.</p>
               <p>But as to our preſent Purpoſe. The firſt Branch of this Power, aſcribed to the Will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> makes the Grace, which we ſtand in moſt need of, to be needleſs. For if the Will can embrace any Object in order to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, upon a common propoſal; there needs no Strength from Grace to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it.</p>
               <p>The other Branch makes all the Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they own, to be fruitleſs, of no effect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meer Cypher, which ſtands for nothing does, can do nothing but at the deſcretion of Free-will. For the Will, when the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is propounded, with what advantage ſoever the Propoſal be made, can always reſiſt and reject it utterly. So that the Grace of God comes to nothing, at the meer humour of mans Free-will.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60922:28"/>
               <p>By the former Branch of the Will's <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency,</hi> the <hi>Power,</hi> in matters of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is from Free-will, and not from Grace: for their Grace gives it no Power at all, but ſuppoſes it there already.</p>
               <p>By the latter Branch, <hi>the Act,</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Salvation, is from the Will, not from Grace: For Grace leaves the Will indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to act or not to act; and therefore its acting is no more from Grace than its not acting; its accepting of Chriſt no more from Grace than its rejecting him.</p>
               <p>Now if both the Power and the Act, in the concerns of Salvation, be from Free-will, and not from Grace; then it is by Free-will, not by Grace, that we are ſaved.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Let us view the <hi>Import</hi> and <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Tendency</hi> of this Doctrine; and then you will ſee ſufficient Reaſon to reject it. Every particular will be an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it; and the particulars are very many.</p>
               <p>(1.) They make <hi>no Grace needfull,</hi> but what was acknowledged by thoſe Perſons who were condemned by the Ancient Church as Enemies of the Grace of Chriſt. <hi>Pelagius,</hi> the Patriarch of the Aſſerters of Free-will, to the prejudice of Divine Grace,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60922:29"/> acknowledged not only a Natural, but a Doctrinal Grace, <hi>viz.</hi> the Word of God diſcovering and propounding that which is good, and perſwading Sinners to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it; <hi>ſuadet omne quod bonum eſt,</hi> it perſwades to all that is good. Here's the ſwaſive Grace of his Modern followers. Nay, he went further, and not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired an external Propoſal of the Object, in the Miniſtry of the Word; but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged an inward Operation of the Spirit, for inlightning the Mind, and exciting the Affections; <hi>Nos ineffabili dono gratiae coeleſtis illuminat,</hi> He inlightens us with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Gift of his heavenly Grace; <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae gloriae magnitudine &amp; praemiorum polici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione accendit:</hi> He inflames us with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Rewards and the greatneſs of the future Glory, and excites the ſtupid Will, by the Revelation of Wiſdom, to Deſires after God. Some of his late followers think it not fit to come ſhort of him in this, but ſeem to require ſome act of the Spirit to inlighten the Mind, and to ſtirr up the Affections. But others of them, moſt applauded and followed; deny all Neceſſity of any immediate Illumination by the Spirit; and tell us, <q>That every one who has the uſe of Reaſon, may,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60922:29"/> without any ſpecial inward Light, very eaſily apprehend whatever in Scripture is neceſſary to be known or believed. <hi>Epiſcop.</hi> And that no imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Operation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Perſpicuit. Script.</hi> theſ. 1. &amp; 3.</note> upon the Mind or Will, is needful for any one that he may Believe.</q> 
                  <hi>Id.</hi> in <hi>Syn. Dor.</hi> p. 200. So that no Grace is needfull with theſe men, but only an external Propoſal by the Word: for what the Word propounds may, without the Light of the Spirit, be ſufficiently underſtood and offered to the Will: and the Will, they ſay, has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably power to embrace whatever is ſo offered by the Underſtanding. If any thing could hinder the Will from embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Good propoſed, it muſt be ſome Corruption in mans Soul, ſome ſtrong Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices or vicious Habits determining the Will unavoidably to that which is evil: but no ſuch thing can be admitted, as they ſtate the Wills liberty. For, as no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Grace, no Operation of the Spirit can determine the Will irreſiſtibly to that which is good, but when it has done its utmoſt, the Will remains free to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary evil: ſo no power of Corruption can determin the Will to any evil, but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60922:30"/> it will remain free to chooſe the contrary good propounded to it.</p>
               <p>The Will of fallen Man, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſuppoſed Corruption in the Soul native or acquired, ſtill retains its primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power intire; only it is under ſome Impediment as to the Exerciſe of it, there is one thing wanting which hinders it from acting, it cannot act without an Object. And this ſignifies no defect or weakneſs in the Will: for the moſt perfect Faculty of Man or Angel in Heaven muſt have a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Object that it may act. Now the Object is offered in the Goſpel, and the Propoſal o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Object by the Goſpel, with the Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tives and Arguments there contained, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the Grace, all the ſupernatural Ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and divine Aſſiſtances, which they thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> requiſite to help the Will, to believe and turn to God. This is to aſcribe leſs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grace than the old <hi>Pelagians</hi> did, who ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were branded by the Church as the capi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal Enemies of ſupernatural Grace, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon that account ſcarce thought worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be called Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>(2.) By their Doctrine, <hi>Grace is give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> according to Merit.</hi> This was the moſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous part of <hi>Pelagianiſm,</hi> which the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church had in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greateſt deteſtation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60922:30"/> and for which <hi>Pelagius</hi> himſelf had been Anathematized, branded with the higheſt Cenſure, by a Synod in <hi>Palaeſtin,</hi> but that he pretended to renounce it.</p>
               <p>Yet Merit, in the ſenſe of that Age, was a far leſs thing, and much more tolerable than the <hi>Papiſts</hi> merit of Condignity. It was not only a good work, of ſuch value and worth in it ſelf, as that a Reward ſhould be due to it in Juſtice; but Merit, as they underſtood it, was any good act which a man did of himſelf, upon the account of which Grace was vouchſafed. This <hi>Bellarmin</hi> himſelf acknowledges, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was concerned to deny it. <q>The Fathers (ſays he) underſtood Grace to be given according to Merit, when any thing is done by our own ſtrength, in reſpect whereof<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Grat. &amp; libr. arbit.</hi> l. 6. c. 5.</note> Grace is given, altho' it be no Merit of Condignity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And in this ſence of <hi>Merit,</hi> the modern Aſſerters of Free-will would have all Grace given, according to Merit. How univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſoever they make Grace to be, yet no man ſhall have it unleſs he merit it. That Grace may be Univerſal, they will have it communicated both to thoſe that are without the Goſpel, and to thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60922:31"/> it. For thoſe who have not the Goſpel, he is ready to give all of them the Grace of the Goſpel, if they will uſe the Light of Nature well; and he does give it actually to thoſe, who by the good uſe of their Free-will, make ſuch an improvement of natural Light. Here the good uſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Light is a good act; and upon the account of that, the Grace of the Goſpel is given, <hi>i. e,</hi> this Grace is given accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Merit, in the ſenſe of the Fathers, who counted it ſo execrable to have it given according to Merit. <hi>Thoſe</hi> (ſay the Remonſtrants) <hi>whom God calleth, and to whom he does vouchſafe the Grace of Preaching, we confeſs, for the moſt part, to be ſuch men, that their Vertues do deſerve no leſs.</hi> Epiſt. contr. Walach. p. 44.</p>
               <p>For thoſe who have the Goſpel, God is ready to give further Grace to them, if they would be worthy Hearers, as they may be, if they would uſe their Free-will well in hearing. <q>But there are ſome worthy hearers of the Goſpel, and ſome unworthy, ſays <hi>Corvinus;</hi> and ſufficient Grace is not given to all promiſcuouſly who hear, <hi>ſed iis qui digni ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> evangelii auditores,</hi> but to thoſe<note place="margin">In <hi>Twiſs. 387.</hi>
                     </note> who are worthy hearers.</q> Which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60922:31"/> is in effect, as tho' he ſpoke out, and ſaid, It is given according to Merit, which is all point blank againſt the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 9. Tit.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
               <p>This they extend to the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all, the <hi>eternal Purpoſe</hi> of God. All the Grace, which is comprized in the Election of Grace, will be ordered according to Merit. Election of particular Perſons depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Faith or Works foreſeen. The Lord foreſees who will believe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will believe, upon the account of this good act he does elect them; ſo they are elected according to Merit. But does he not purpoſe from Eternity to give Faith in time? No, by no means; for if he had decreed this, they would be under ſome Neceſſity to believe; and ſuch Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is not conſiſtent with the Liberty of mans Will. Therefore it muſt be left to their Free-will whether they ſhall believe or no: and when God foreſees that they ſhall make ſo good uſe of their Free-will as to believe, then upon that account he elects them. In plain Engliſh, he chooſes thoſe, whom he foreſees will merit the Election of Grace by the good uſe of Free-will.</p>
               <p>Nay, all the Grace, in the great and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60922:32"/> precious Promiſes, and in the whole Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, will be according to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For they will have the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſuſpended upon ſome Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſuch a condition, as is to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meerly by the power of Free-will, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by no Grace at all, but that gentle excitement which they call <hi>Swaſion,</hi> which enables not the Will to perform the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but plainly ſpeaks it able before hand. Such a condition performed is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Cauſe, a moving and engaging Cauſe, and no leſs Merit, than that which the ancient Church condemned in <hi>Pelagius.</hi> For it is a good Act performed by our own ſtrength, upon the account of which the Grace of the Covenant is vouchſafed, which a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> will not deny to be the Merit that is under the Curſe and Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Synods and Fathers twelve hundred years agoe. Their other Principles over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Grace of God, and lay it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; but this quite deſtroyes it, and makes it no Grace, if the Apoſtles arguing be good Reaſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 6.</p>
               <p>(3.) This Doctrine (which owns no more Grace, and aſcribes ſo much to Free-will) makes God not to be the worke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or real Cauſe of the ſpiritual and ſaving
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60922:32"/> bleſſings of Converſion and Regeneration, nor the Author and Giver of Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Holineſs. Theſe are rather to be aſcribed to Man, than unto God. This will appear,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In <hi>general.</hi> Converſion, Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sanctification, Perſeverance, and what elſe of this nature is required to our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, is to be attributed to a mans ſelf, more than the Spirit of Grace; they are the Effects and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chievements of Free-will, rather than of Grace.</p>
               <p>A man Converts and quickens himſelf, Regenerates and begets himſelf, Creates himſelf ſo far as he is a New Creature, and upholds himſelf when he is created. This ſeems ſtrange and uncouth (not to ſay abſurd and horrid); but there is plain Reaſon for it, ſuch as may convince any who will yield to evident Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Grace, however conſidered, (either in <hi>Election,</hi> or <hi>Redemption,</hi> or the <hi>Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits Operations</hi>) does no more for the quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening and Regenerating of thoſe who are converted, than it does for thoſe who are never converted; therefore it is not Grace, but ſomething elſe, that does the work. If the Lord had done no more for the making of this World, than for making
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60922:33"/> of other Worlds that were never made, the Creation of the World could never have been aſcribed to him. If Chriſt had done no more to raiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the dead, than he did to raiſe others who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued dead in their Graves, he could not have been ſaid to raiſe him to Life. He that does no more towards the effecting of a thing, than when it is not done at all, he cannot be ſaid to do it. Now Grace does no more for the quickening of thoſe that are alive to God, than for thoſe who are ſtill dead and will be ſo for ever. Therefore it is not Grace that does the work; it muſt be aſcribed to ſomething elſe, not to the Spirit of Grace, but to a mans ſelf, and his own Free-will.</p>
               <p>This is evident in the Nature, viſible in the very Complexion of their <hi>Moral Grace.</hi> This (which is all the Grace they own) conſiſts in Swaſive Propoſals. Now he that only perſwades or propounds the doing of a thing, does not thereby do it at all, but would have you to do it your ſelves, and ſuppoſes you can if you will. So that this is the plain Import of their Doctrine, that men can convert and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken themſelves, and do it if it be done. However any be ſaid to be <hi>born of God,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60922:33"/> yet they may beget themſelves. However they be ſaid to be <hi>the Lords Workmanſhip, created of Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, ver.</hi> 10. yet they are their own Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and make themſelves new Creatures. However the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>ver. 1. You hath he quickned,</hi> yet indeed they raiſe themſelves to life. And ſince they do it themſelves, to themſelves they may in all reaſon aſcribe it, and accordingly glory in it. The Crown is not to be caſt at the ſeet of him who ſits on the Throne. Grace is to have neither Throne nor Crown; that is to have the Crown which does the work; Free-will does it, and this muſt wear it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. More <hi>particularly,</hi> it is manifeſt, that they make not God to be the <hi>real cauſe</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſaving works,</hi> or the giver of thoſe Spiritual Bleſſings; becauſe by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine neither the Power nor the Act can be aſcribed to him: For they ſay he does nothing to this purpoſe but by vertue of Moral Grace: And it is evident, that this, or He by this, gives neither the Power nor he Act, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(1.) <hi>Swaſive Grace,</hi> or the Lord by ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive Propoſals, gives no man power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieve or turn to God; it rather ſuppoſes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60922:34"/> that he has it already before or without this Grace. The vertue of it (of all the Grace they own) is only that of Advice or Suaſion; and no man reaſonably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades or adviſes another to be able, but only to be willing to uſe what already he has. He that holds forth a Light to a Man lying on the ground, and moves him with Arguments to riſe and walk, does not thereby give him Legs and Strength, but ſuppoſes he has theſe already, if he would uſe them. He that only ſhews another what he has to doe, and offers reaſon to perſwade him to do it, not taking any other courſe to ſtrengthen him for it, takes it for granted that he is afore-hand able for it. Now this is all that their Moral Grace pretends to; it ſhews the Sinner that it is his Duty to turn to God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and uſes Arguments to move him to it, but gives no other ſtrength for it than what this Advice includes, which as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion or Advice does indeed give none at all, but plainly ſuppoſes it in being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They ſay, a Sinner, under the Influence of this Moral Grace, is able to Convert and Regenerate himſelf, to beget himſelf to a New Life. But if he be able, his Ability is from Nature; and the Power
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60922:34"/> of his natural Faculties was not from Grace, ſeeing this their Grace is not for the giving of Ability where it is not, but only for exciting it where it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51-100" type="pages">
               <p>(2.) As <hi>the Power</hi> for theſe great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Salvation is not from God or his Grace, ſo neither is <hi>the Act</hi> from him. For, 1. That which gives or works the Act, <hi>determins the Will,</hi> or cauſes it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin it ſelf; but the Lord by this Grace (which is all they own) brings it only to the Wills choice, and leaves it to do as it liſt, and ſo plainly leaves the Act to it ſelf; ſo that if the Soul do actually Believe, or Repent, or turn to God, this is of it ſelf: their Grace leaves the Will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to act or not to act, and ſo no more works the one than the other, and is no more the Cauſe that it acts, than that it acts not. It leaves it to the Will, either to yield or refuſe; if it yield, it is not from Grace, but the Will. Grace leaves it in the Power of the Will to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; if it reſiſt not, it is from the Will, not from Grace. The Lord by his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er works not the Will to turn to God, to love, to embrace Chriſt, to yield to the Spirit; but leaves it indifferent to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60922:35"/> turn to God or againſt him, to love God or to hate him, to embrace Chriſt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him, to yield to the Spirit or reſiſt him. It muſt be left indifferent as to either, Grace turns not the Scales, but leaves the Will at an equal poiſe, that the Will of Man, not the Grace of God, may have the caſting weight; if Grace ſhould weigh it down, the Liberty of the Will, they ſay, would be violated, and its Nature deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyed.</p>
               <p>(3.) Nay, their Grace is ſo far from working the Will to actual Faith or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, that by their account it ſeems to <hi>lead a man into Sin,</hi> and <hi>leave</hi> him in it: for it is a Sin for a man to be Indifferent whether he Believe or Believe not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he accept Chriſt or reject him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he love or hate him: But all that this Grace does to the Will, is to bring it to ſuch an Indifferency; and ſo the Grace of God with them does no other, no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Office for a Sinner, than to bring his Soul into a wicked Poſture; and in that Poſture it does and muſt leave the Will to it ſelf; and there left, if the Will be no better to it ſelf than Grace is, or can be, it ſhall never come into a better Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60922:35"/>
               <p>Nay further, the Lord is ſo far from Determining the Will, and ſo from cauſing the Act by making it willing; that it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> for him to do it. They ſay (as was ſhewed before) that the Will cannot be determined by God himſelf without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying it; they will have it an Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency, and to imply a Contradiction. And thus the Lord is ſo far from being the Worker or real Cauſe of actual Faith, Converſion, Sanctification, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould be the Cauſe thereof; he is ſo far from actually working theſe, that he cannot do it.</p>
               <p>Let me but add one Argument more. This Grace is given <hi>equally to all,</hi> and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects no more in one than another; and therefore can be no more the Cauſe of actual Converſion in thoſe that turn to God, than in thoſe that are never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; works Regeneration no more in thoſe that are ſanctified, than in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate; <hi>i. e.</hi> works it not at all, is no Cauſe of it. The Lord, by vertue of this Grace, gives actual Faith and Repentance no more to thoſe that Believe and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, than to ſuch as perſevere in Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency and Unbelief: gave Faith no more to <hi>Paul</hi> than to <hi>Judas,</hi> Repentance no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60922:36"/> more to <hi>Peter</hi> than to <hi>Simon Magus; i. e.</hi> he gives it not at all.</p>
               <p>This is the clear <hi>conſequence</hi> of their Doctrine. The Lord is not the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Finiſher</hi> of our Faith, or of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; nor the real Cauſe of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Sanctification, and other ſaving Bleſſings; and ſo, not the Author of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. It is not <hi>by his Grace,</hi> but of <hi>our ſelves,</hi> both as to the Power and the Act, in direct oppoſition to the Text and the whole ſtrain of the Goſpel. And it is as reconcileable with Scripture and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of God, to ſay he is not the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of the World, or the Author of any thing; as to ſay he is not the Author or real Cauſe of thoſe great Concerns of Salvation.</p>
               <p>(4.) This leads them to deny <hi>Original Sin.</hi> They muſt of neceſſity make little or nothing of the Corruption of our Nature, ſince they will have their Swaſive Grace to be a ſufficient Relief againſt it; as if all the Sin in mans Nature could be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued out of him without more adoe, and all the Power of Corruption, natural and contracted too, might be effectually ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued and crucified by rational Advice; whereas this Moral Swaſion is of it ſelf of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60922:36"/> no Efficacy at all for this purpoſe, and appears to be ſo in that it effects no ſuch thing in far the greateſt part of thoſe who partake of it as much as any, but leaves them altogether as corrupt as it found them.</p>
               <p>I cannot diſcern, that they will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any corruption at all to be in the Will, tho Scripture and Experience ſhew that it is moſt of all there. The Will ſeems to be now as ſound (by their Doctrine) as it was in Innocency; nor ſtands it in need of more help by Grace, than <hi>Adam</hi> before the Fall: for then he had and needed Swaſive Grace. <hi>In the day that thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt dye:</hi> Here is the Duty propounded, and the Propoſal inforced with a powerful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by God himſelf; that is the ſum of Swaſive Grace, which the Lord ſeeing needfull for our firſt Parents, did thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter it, as far from Corruption as it was then. And if the Will need no more now, it is as free from Corruption as it was then. Thus for the Affections, there muſt be no more Corruption in them than in the Will, theſe being but the Acts and Motions of it. Or, if they will conſider them as in the Senſitive Appetite; yet
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60922:37"/> common Illumination is enough to heal it there: for thereby the Affections are ſufficiently excited and quickened. Nor is there any Depravation in the Mind, but what may be cured by common Light, ſuch as the moſt corrupt and wicked men have.</p>
               <p>That which admits ſo eaſie a Cure muſt needs be ſleight and little; and that little too, which they acknowledge, is with them neither Sin nor Puniſhment proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo not evil at all, unleſs there be ſome evil which is neither. The Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Natures by the Fall, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be aggravated in Scripture, is not in their account properly either our Sin or our Puniſhment; but only our Infeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; and no great Infelicity neither, ſince with them it can be neither ſpiritual Death, nor mortal Diſeaſe, no nor very conſiderable Weakneſs. For if it were ſuch a Weakneſs, no Grace would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair it but that which communicates an anſwerable Strength. But that Grace which they think ſufficient to repair all, gives not any ſtrength at all, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes there is Power enough in Nature to Recover it ſelf, if it be but excited.</p>
               <p>This in a manner makes Chriſt of none
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60922:37"/> effect. The great end of his coming was to Reſtore our Natures fallen from God, and made uncapable of honouring and injoying him: Therefore he took our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and performed and ſuffered ſo much therein. But what need all this waſte, if we can lick our ſelves whole by vertue of a little common Light? and ſo little not needfull with ſome of them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Peccat. Orig.</hi> c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The great <hi>Auguſtin</hi> reduces the whole Chriſtian Doctrine to two Heads, the Knowledge of the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> and the Knowledge of the <hi>Second:</hi> What we ſuffered by <hi>Adam,</hi> and what we gained by <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But tho theſe be Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in the <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> how little they ſtand for in the Doctrine of <hi>Free-will,</hi> we may hereby perceive. And it will be further manifeſt by another Fundamental, which, depending on this now inſiſted on, falls with it.</p>
               <p>(5.) By this Doctrine there is no need of <hi>Regeneration.</hi> To be Regenerate, is in the Language of the Holy Ghoſt to be <hi>born of God, Joh.</hi> 1. 13. to be <hi>born again,</hi> or <hi>born from above, Joh.</hi> 3. 3. and that is to receive a Principle of Spiritual Life and Motion from God. <hi>Vid. Ham.</hi> in <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 13. But no ſuch Principle is neceſſary
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60922:38"/> in the Will, which indeed moſt needs it. But no Habit of Holineſs is planted there, no good Quality created in it by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; that they ſay is a neceſſitating Act, and would be prejudicial to its Liberty. The Image of God needs no repairing in the Heart or Will, tho' that be the chief Receptacle and Subject of it; even the Schoolmen making this the principal Seat of all Vertues. It needs no ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Principle or Quality, to incline it to that which is good; they will have it able of it ſelf, by its own native Power, to embrace any good, how ſupernatural ſoever, which the Mind offers to it. It can produce the beſt Acts, without any inward Principle ſuitable or proportionable to them. The Tree need not be good, that the Fruit may be good; or rather, it is good enough already, it is ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally. The Will or Heart of Man (how naught ſoever the Scripture ſpeaks it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting it to be <hi>deſperately wicked, Jer.</hi> 17. 9. and the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 19.) ſeems by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to be as good by Nature, as God can or will make it; no worſe than it was when firſt formed. It loſt no ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Qualities or Accompliſhments by the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60922:38"/> Fall: for it had none before.<note place="margin">Collat. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. p. 248. <hi>In ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ali morte non ſeparantur pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè dona ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualia ab homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis voluntate,</hi> &amp;c.</note> So that all regenerating Grace as to the Will is clearly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered. Nor will they allow any new Qualities to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed by the Spirit of Grace into the Mind or Affections,<note place="margin">Syn. Dor. 196.</note> no more than into the Will: for that they ſay is repugnant to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Means of Salvation. All that they think requiſite, is common Light, ſuch as they deny not to the vileſt men (nor can well deny to Devils: for they diſcern the truth and goodneſs of what is propoſed in the Goſpel); by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are help of ſuch Light, their own Wills can regenerate them, ſo far as they think any Regeneration needfull. I find it no eaſie thing to diſcern what their Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is. The beſt I can make of it is this. The Mind needs no new Birth or Life, but what it has from common Light; nor do the Affections need any exciting or quickening but what that ſame effects. But tho they count this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quickening, they do not call it Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation: for many, thus quickened, do live and dye unregenerate. It is an act of the Will muſt do the work, and for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60922:39"/> that the Will muſt be left to it ſelf. The Spirit of God muſt not touch it, muſt not give it any Principle of Life, muſt not act it by any ſpecial or immediate Influence; but if of its own accord it turn it ſelf to that which is good, the Sinner is thereby born again. So that Regeneration is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated by a little common Light, ſuch as the Children of Darkneſs have, and an act of Free-will, without any further aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, any other work of the Spirit in or upon it.</p>
               <p>Thus, by this one act of Free-will at firſt, they are regenerated <hi>actually;</hi> and afterwards, by repeated acts of Free-will, they may be regenerated <hi>habitually:</hi> for, the Will, by repeated Acts, can beget gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Habits, and ſo help them to habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Regeneration; tho they deny the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Grace can work in them any ſuch thing as Habits or Principles of Holineſs. Now, this is to be <hi>born again of the Will of Man,</hi> not <hi>of the Will of God, Joh.</hi> 1. 13. The Scripture declares, that they who are Regenerate, are <hi>born of God, 1 Joh. 3. 9. born of the Spirit,</hi> Joh. 3. 8. but this is to be born of Free-will, not of God, nor of the Spirit, unleſs Free-will be God or the Spirit. The Apoſtle ſays, <hi>of his own
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60922:39"/> Will begat he us,</hi> Jam. 1. 18. but they muſt ſay, Of their own Wills they beget themſelves. Yet, this is all the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which they count neceſſary, and ſo make that New-birth a needleſs thing, which the Scripture calls for and deſcribes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y other Characters, and declares all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to the Kingdom of Heaven impoſſible without it.</p>
               <p>(6.) This takes Sinners off from that which is <hi>really ſaving,</hi> and leads them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake up with that which falls ſhort of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. It teaches them to reſt ſatisfied with ſuch a Faith, a Repentance, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſion, a Regeneration, as common Light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd rational Propoſals (ſuch as every one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eets with in the Miniſtry of the Word) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſufficient to effect. But theſe alone can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever produce any ſaving Faith or Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance, any ſaving Regeneration or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſion</p>
               <p>Thoſe who perſwade them, that this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nough for thoſe ſaving Effects, go about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o delude Sinners; and if they look after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o more, their Souls are like to be ruined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ever. Moral Grace may perhaps pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ail for ſome Morality; but this alone can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever be effectual, to turn a <hi>Heart of ſtone</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to a <hi>Heart of fleſh,</hi> to turn the Enmity
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60922:40"/> of the Will into Love to Chriſt, to turn Sinners from the Power of Satan unto God, to raiſe the Soul to Life that is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually dead, to make them new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are not the Effects of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gentle Swaſion, but of an Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. They mean ſomething elſe than Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture intends by theſe Expreſſions, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make theſe ſaving works ſo low, commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and eaſie things, and ſo much in the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and at the beck of a Sinners corrupte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Will. Nothing more ruines Souls, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſting in that <hi>as ſaving</hi> which is not ſo and when Divines promote the Deluſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how pernicious is it like to prove?</p>
               <p>(7.) It deſtroyes <hi>holy Obedience,</hi> inwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and outward. Leaves no place for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exerciſe of Grace in the Heart, or wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truely good in the Converſation. It pluc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up theſe by the roots, taking away h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bitual Regeneration which is the root <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, the exerciſe of Grace in the acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of an inward gracious Principle; but the ſay there is no ſuch Principle planted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Heart or Will by the Spirit of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lineſs; and where the Principle is not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cannot be acted. There can be no vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Acts, where there is no vital Principle that which is not alive, cannot put for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60922:40"/> Acts of life. Or, to uſe the terms where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt expreſſes it, <hi>the Fruit is not good, unleſs the Tree be good.</hi> No good Acts can be produced by the Heart or Will, till it ſelf be good. It is not, it cannot be good, when there are no good Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in it. It had no good, no holy Qualities planted in it by the Spirit of Grace; that, (with them) only acts Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and does no more ſanctifie thoſe that are holy, than thoſe that are profane. So that, if the Will have any goodneſs, any thing that is holy in it; it has it from it ſelf, not from the Spirit of Holineſs. Thus the Fruits of the Spirit will be no other, than the Fruits of Free-will; of Free-will unſanctified, unleſs it ſanctifie it ſelf: and the acts of Obedience will be no other, than the acts of natural Morality, ſuch as Mans degenerate Will can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce by its natural Power, without any aſſiſtance, but that of Moral or ſwaſive Grace; which begets no good Qualities, gives no inward ſtrength, affords no help of any kind, more to thoſe who do moſt, than to thoſe who do nothing at all.</p>
               <p>We need not wonder, if thoſe of this Perſwaſion ſhould ſatisfie themſelves, and would have others ſatisfied with ſuch a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60922:41"/> Morality; their Principles do afford, and can require nothing better. But whether the Acts of it be thoſe gracious Acts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thoſe Fruits of the Spirit, thoſe good works, which the Scripture ſo much calls for, and makes the Way to Salvation; let thoſe conſider who are concerned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the Way to Salvation.</p>
               <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y charge their Oppoſers, for not preſſing Moral Duties. If they mean there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Practical Chriſtianity, there are none in the World preſs it more. But we are not for a Pagan, but a Chriſtian Morality; and think it not adviſeable to preſs exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Acts alone, without minding the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Root, from whence all that is truely Chriſtian muſt ſpring. We count it abſurd and prepoſterous to look for Fruits where there is no Root, for gracious Acts where Grace is not planted in the Heart. They may deck a May-pole with as many Garlands as they pleaſe, and ſet off a Maſt with Flags and Streamers; but they will never thereby make them Fruit-trees. The Lord will condemn thoſe who bring not forth good Fruit; and thoſe alſo who lead them in a way, where they are never like to be truely fruitfull, without better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60922:41"/>
               <p>(8.) This <hi>ſtifles Love to God,</hi> takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that which is the Foundation and Ground of a ſpecial tranſcendent Love to him. That which is the riſe of our Love to God, is <hi>his Love to us, 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 19. it is this that kindles our Affection to him, and raiſes Love into a Flame: But he that believes and conſiders, that God had no more thoughts of Love for him from Eternity, than he had for thoſe who are under his everlaſting Hatred; and that Chriſt had no more Love for him in the work of Redemption; did Obey, Suffer, Satisfie, Purchaſe no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or him, than he did for thoſe who were in Hell, when he Suffered; and that the Spirit of Grace does no more for him, in order to his Salvation, than he does for the Veſſels of Wrath, ſitted for Deſtruction; will ſcarce find any thing in the Love of God (on this Conſideration) to engage his Soul to a ſpecial Love for God: He will be in danger to Love God with no more than a common Love, ſuch as a carnal Man may have; who believes that the Lord loves him no more, than he loves thoſe who are to be tormented for ever with the Devil and his Angels. He will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind a Motive from hence, to hug and love
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60922:42"/> himſelf rather than God: For, when that which they call Love in God, ſeems but an indifferent reſpect, not intending more good to one than another, but as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves determine it; he had got no ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al benefit, no particular advantage by that Love, if he had not been better to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: The Lord, as they repreſent him, (whatever is pretended concerning the greatneſs and univerſality of his Love to Mankind) ſeems indifferent as to Love or Hatred, as to the Happineſs or Miſery of Man. The Lord left it indifferent, in his eternal Purpoſe, whether any ſhould be Saved or no; and Chriſt, in the Work of Redemption, left it indifferent whether any ſhould be actually Redeemed or no; and the Spirit, in Calling Sinners, leaves it indifferent whether any be effectually Called or no: There was no Affection in all this, but what might have ended in Love or Hatred, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the Damning of all, as ſoon as the Saving of any. That which determines this indifference, and makes it prove Love, is the Sinner him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the good uſe of his Free-will: Had it not been for this, for any Love that God had for him, for any expreſſion of it from Father, Son, or Spirit, he had
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60922:42"/> been one of the Children of Wrath, in the ſame Condemnation with others. So that the plain tendency of their Doctrine, is to lead Sinners to reflect affectionately on themſelves, but with Indifferency upon God.</p>
               <p>Such is the <hi>general Love</hi> which they will have in God to Mankind; it is but an indifferent reſpect to all; which proves Love or Hatred, as the Sinners Will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines it. But when they aſcribe any particular Love to God, it is no other than what ariſes from the Sinners Love to him: He foreſaw that we would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and ſo love him, and therefore he intended Life for us: He foreſaw that we would embrace and chooſe Chriſt, and therefore did he chooſe us. So that God did not <hi>Love us firſt,</hi> but we him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Apoſtle ſays, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 10, 19. He did not <hi>Chooſe us firſt,</hi> but we did Chooſe him, whatever Chriſt ſays, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 16. Thus they ſtop up the Spring of our Love to God, they deſtroy the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and raze the ground of our Love to him, if that be it which the Apoſtle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. It is the greatneſs, the riches, the freeneſs of Divine Love that ingages, that conſtrains us to Love him: But this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60922:43"/> not only defaces the Riches and Freeneſs, but in a manner takes away the true Naure and Notion of his Love, when it makes it an Affection ſo indifferent to Mans Happineſs or Miſery.</p>
               <p>(9.) It <hi>deſtroys the Exerciſe of Faith,</hi> and takes them off from a continued de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on God, and truſting in him. It is inconſiſtent with that Life of Faith, which muſt be the Life of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               <p>This takes them off from depending on God, both in their <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Concerns, and in common and <hi>humane</hi> Affairs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For <hi>thoſe Affairs</hi> which depend on the <hi>Wills of other Men:</hi> They cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on God for the ordering of them; for none are to depend on him for things which are not at his diſpoſal: But the Wills of Men, and ſo the Affairs which depend thereon, are not (with them) at Gods diſpoſal; ſince, by their Principles, he cannot ſway their Wills effectually one way or other; for this, in their Account, is to deſtroy their natural Liberty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to <hi>ſpiritual Concerns,</hi> for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Grace, or the means of Grace effectual. For the Promoting of Holineſs, for the Growth or Exerciſe of it, or for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60922:43"/> Perſeverance in it, there is no need to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on God: For it is not neceſſary to depend on another for that which is in his own Power. Now theſe things, and the like, are in the Power of his own Will; he is the Maſter of them, if he will not be wanting to himſelf. Indeed it is more in their own Power, than in the Power of God; for every Mans Will can determine it ſelf to theſe things, but God cannot, without deſtroying the Will: For if he determine it, he leaves it not indifferent; and if it be not indifferent, it is not free; and if it be not free, it is not an humane Will: And therefore they have more reaſon to depend on themſelves, where they believe the Power is, than on God, where they ſay it is not. If there be any reaſon to rely on God, it is for further continuance of that which they call ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Grace: But there is no more need to depend on him for this, than the other; for this is never withdrawn, unleſs they be contumacious, and obſtinately reſiſt it: But then it is in their Power not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, but comply with it; and if they will not, God cannot help it: For when he has put forth all the Operations of his Grace upon the Soul, the Will is at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60922:44"/> and has Power to do as it liſt. The Power is moſt in Man ſtill; and where the Power is, there muſt be the Dependance, upon themſelves rather than upon God; though this Self-dependance be under the Curſe of God in Scripture, and plainly deſerves his heavyeſt Curſe.</p>
               <p>(10.) It <hi>overthrows Humility and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> One may ſmell from whence it comes, by the rank Tendency of it to Pride and Self-exaltation. The deſign of the Goſpel is clearly to debaſe man, and take from him all occaſion of Boaſting or Glorying in himſelf; or of aſcribing the Praiſe, either of his State or Actions, to himſelf, <hi>Rom. 3. 9. 27. 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 29, 30. But this Doctrine obliges a Believer to aſcribe the difference, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and others who are in the State of Sin and Miſery, not unto Grace, but to himſelf; leaves him no ground to imagine that it was Grace which made the difference.</p>
               <p>Grace is, with them, indifferently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded unto all Sinners under the Goſpel at leſt. Others had the ſame Light, the ſame rational Propoſals, with as much Clearneſs and Earneſtneſs, in the ſame Degree, and of no leſs Power and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60922:44"/> it is common in all reſpects. That which is every way common and indifferent, could not poſſibly make us to differ. But when they had it in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, this man would make good uſe of it, without any other help from Grace than the reſt had; they would not. His Will complyed with the Propoſal; their Wills, no leſs aſſiſted than his, reſiſted. Grace brought it equally to the choice of their Wills, and there left it: His Will determined it ſelf to comply; their Wills determined againſt it: that made the difference, not Grace, which was alike in all; but Free-will, which he uſed better than Others. If my Will (may he ſay) had not been better to me than Grace, it had been as bad with me as them: For Grace was as good to them as me. The Apoſtle asks, <hi>Who made thee to differ? 1 Cor.</hi> 4. 7. ſuppoſing none would have the Confidence to arrogate this to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But he that is for Free-will muſt ſay, <hi>I made my ſelf to differ.</hi> Grace brought it to the choice of my Will, whether there ſhould be any difference or no; it does no more for any; if there be any difference made, it is Free-will that makes it. Thoſe of them that are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60922:45"/> as to uſe plain dealing, ſpeak out, and ſay expreſly, <hi>Ego me diſcerno,</hi> I make the difference my ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſays, <hi>By the Grace of God I am what I am,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. but they muſt ſay, <hi>By the good uſe of Free-will I am what I am:</hi> For Grace is ſuch a thing (with them) as moves all, affects all, leaves all alike: If any one be better than another, as to ſtate or actings, it is not Grace that makes him ſo, for the worſt have as much of their Grace as the beſt; the difference muſt be aſcribed to Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. Nor can their Doctrine ſhew them any Reaſon, why they ſhould not aſcribe it to themſelves, and glory in it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever become of the Glory of Divine Grace.</p>
               <p>(11.) It makes it <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, to Pray for themſelves or others,</hi> for thoſe things which we ſhould moſt of all Pray for: This is evident enough, in that it leaves not place for Faith and Dependance on God, in common Affairs, or ſpiritual Concerns, as was ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For we are not to Pray to God, but where we may rely and depend on him; nor ſeek him for what we may not truſt him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14, But further,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60922:45"/> the things that Chriſtians are principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Pray for, are ſpiritual and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bleſſings; theſe are all comprized in, or depend upon Grace. Let us ſee how favourable their Principles are to Praying for Grace, either effectual or preventing.</p>
               <p>As to the former, they need not Pray for Efficacious Grace, for it is in their own Power to make it effectual; and who needs beg that of another, which he has in his own Power? Their Grace is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual in the Soul, when it becomes willing, (for then it has its effect;) but with them, nothing is more in their Power and Will, than to be willing: And it is needleſs and ſenſeleſs to Pray to God to make them will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>i. e.</hi> to make Grace effectual, when they can do it well enough of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de Nat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Grat. <hi>c. 18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quid eſt ſtultius, quam or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ut facias quod in poteſtate habes?</hi> What more fooliſh, than to Pray God thou mayeſt do that which thou haſt in thine own Power? And elſewhere, <hi>Ne fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus homines,</hi> &amp;c. Let us not deceive Men, for we cannot deceive God: We Pray not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o God at all, but only feign that we Pray, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f we think that our ſelves, not He, doth what we Pray for.</p>
               <p>And as they need not, ſo they muſt not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60922:46"/> Pray, that God would make Grace effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, or make it work effectually in them for God cannot do it, and they muſt no ſeek that of him which he cannot do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> To make Grace effectual, is of unwilling to make them willing, to determine th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Will to what he Propoſes; but this (the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay) he cannot do, without invading it freedom: All that he can do, is to Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, and leave the Will to do as it likes if he ſhould bow it effectually one way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other, that would be a breach upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liberty which is eſſential to it; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beg this of him, would be to ſeek an i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſibility. So that, unleſs they will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abſurd, they muſt not Pray that God woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> effectually bow or incline their Wills, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> believe in Chriſt, to turn to God, to lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, to fear him, to walk in his way to hate Sin, or mortifie it; yea, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> avoid it. They muſt not Pray, that Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would effectually ſubdue their Wills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Will in any thing: For, to be ſo ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jected, though to God, and by a Divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Motion, is not conſiſtent with that Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom which the Nature of the Will r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quires.</p>
               <p>If their Petitions be of ſuch Import, (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the beſt Petitions of Chriſtians are) the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60922:46"/> Prayers contradict their Principles; their Prayers are a Plea for the Truth which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey diſpute againſt. Whatever they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with Men, yet they muſt be for us, when they have to do with God, if they will have any thing to do with God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Prayer, or Pray any thing like Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tians.</p>
               <p>As for preventing or ſufficient Grace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey need not Pray for that; for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave it already, or they will have it, thô <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey Pray not for it; for all have it, even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe who never Pray while they live.</p>
               <p>But if they ſhould Pray for it, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etitions muſt bear ſuch a ſence as will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e very harſh to any Chriſtian or ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Ear. Sufficient Grace is that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nables a Man to turn to God if he will. So, this muſt be it they Pray for: Lord, give me ſuch Grace, that I may Love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee if I will, that I may Fear thee if I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt, that I may Obey thee if I pleaſe. This Grace leaves, and muſt leave the Will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, to chooſe or refuſe, to act or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot to act, at its Pleaſure: For ſo far the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord may by his Grace proceed with the Will, but no farther, without intrenching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n its Liberty: So that it is this which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ray for; Lord, give me ſuch Grace, as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60922:47"/> will leave me Indifferent, either to Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Hate thee; either to Turn or not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Turn unto thee; to Obey or Rebell again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee; either to Believe in Chriſt, or to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Unbeliever: This muſt be the Impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of their Prayers for Grace, if they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſiſtent with their Principles: But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they will Pray with the ſenſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians or ſober Men, they muſt renounc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Doctrine of Free-will.</p>
               <p>Further, They muſt not Pray for other more than themſelves: Not for En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies, that God would effectually Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Hearts, that they may not Oppreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Perſecute, Obſtruct the Goſpel, Oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſts Intereſt. They muſt not Pray f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Children, Friends, Strangers; that Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would effectually Turn them to himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he would Create in them new Heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Inſpire their Wills with gracious Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples; that he would conquer their r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bellious Wills, or not leave them in a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacity to reſiſt him, or reject the Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Grace. They muſt not Pray for them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves or others, that God will give the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any Grace, but what will leave it at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> choice and arbitrement of their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wills (when there is no good Qualit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in them) as well to reſiſt as not to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60922:47"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Grace, before Converſion; as well to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xpel as to retain it, after Converſion.</p>
               <p>Prayer is ſuch an acknowledgment of God, ſo eſſential to all Religion, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut it there can be no Religion, either Chriſtian or Natural; therefore ſo far as his Doctrine makes it unneceſſary or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſonable to Pray, ſo far it tends to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irpate all Religion.</p>
               <p>(12.) It is inconſiſtent with <hi>that Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulneſs</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> which ſhould make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p the Life of a Chriſtian; with thoſe Praiſes, whereby God is glorified in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pecial manner, and which muſt be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mployment of Eternity. It is the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngrateful Doctrine that ever any under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Name of Chriſtians entertained: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereby, he that is in the ſtate of Grace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as no more Cauſe on that account to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thankful to God, than he that is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſtate of Sin and Damnation: For he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not obliged to be thankful for more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han he has received; and the beſt Saint, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſuch, has received no more from God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes no more to his Grace, than he that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontinues the worſt of Sinners. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is in a happier Condition, is from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imſelf, and the good uſe of his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. Grace was common, afforded him
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60922:48"/> and others indifferently; it was his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Free-will that made the difference, ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as there is any. Nay, a Saint in Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will, by their Doctrine, have no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon to be Praiſing God, or Admirin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, than one in Hell: But of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hereafter.</p>
               <p>The recovery of Man out of the ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Sin and Miſery, into which he is fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en, either by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Wickedneſs; is more to be aſcribed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf, than unto God; and ſo he ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more thanks to himſelf for it, than to Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> He does more to Convert, to Quicken, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sanctifie, to Eſtabliſh, to Save himſelf, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God does by his Grace; and ſo he has mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon to thank himſelf for all. The Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> does very little, in compariſon of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Man does in theſe great Concerns; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that little which God does, would co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to nothing at all, if Man himſelf did n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> give it efficacy, and make ſomething <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it: So that there is left very little grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or occaſion of giving Praiſe and Glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, where, if for any thing, the hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt Praiſe and Glory is eternally due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, and where above all he deſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the greateſt Praiſe and Glory to himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> There ſeems much more occaſion to aſcrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60922:48"/> the Praiſe and Glory of Mans Salvation, both on Earth and in Heaven, unto Man himſelf: Not unto thee, O Lord, muſt they ſay, not unto thee, but unto our ſelves be the Praiſe, or at leaſt more unto our ſelves than unto thee. View this Doctrine well, and compare it with the Doctrine and Deſign of the Goſpel, and you will find them juſt as agreeable as Light and Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>(13.) It <hi>tempts men ſtrongly to neglect God</hi> and their <hi>Souls,</hi> to live in any Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs their Inclination leads them to, and not to break off a Courſe of Sin by ſpeedy Repentance: For their pretended ſufficient Grace is univerſal, and denied to none; that brings Repentance to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mans power and choice, he has Grace enough to repent if he will. And ſince it is in his own Power, he may take his own time for it, and need not fear to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf with the Pleaſures or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Sin.</p>
               <p>What is to be feared, to reſtrain them here from the Practice of Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs? unleſs they will ſay, that common Grace being abuſed, may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, and the Sinner by the Judgment of God given up to Obduration. Here
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60922:49"/> would be ſome danger indeed, if that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration did irreſiſtably determine the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Will to ſuch Wickedneſs: But there is no fear of that; for, by their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples the Will cannot be ſo determined, either to good or evil; it is inconſiſtent with that Liberty which is eſſential to it, and which it cannot want while it is a Will. Therefore no light can be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, no hardneſs can be contracted; but the Will muſt ſtill be at liberty, to turn to God or not to turn, to repent or not to repent, at pleaſure. They have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, from their Principles, to go on in their evil ways, 'till they be in danger to live no longer; and then it is not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, if God will give them Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; they have enough for that in their own Power, and may repent and turn to God when they liſt. Accordingly, one of the prime Aſſerters of this Doctrine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admoniſhed of his Debauches, made this return; I am a Child of the Devil to day, but I have Free-will, and to morrow I will make my ſelf a Child of God.</p>
               <p>(14.) It <hi>deſtroys Juſtification of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> all Juſtification of Sinners, which the Goſpel gives notice of: It will have us Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, not by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60922:49"/> or of God, but our own Righteouſneſs; by our own Righteouſneſs, in the fulleſt and groſſeſt ſenſe; by a Righteouſneſs which is in our ſelves, and of our ſelves, and by our ſelves: By our own acts or works, not Performed by the help of any ſpecial Grace, but by the Power of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.</p>
               <p>Their Juſtification is thus ſtated: The act of Faith (or ſincere Obedience, or inherent Holineſs) though it be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, yet is accepted of God inſtead of a perfect Righteouſneſs; and ſo by it we are Juſtified, as if it were a perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. Now thoſe acts of Faith, or Obedience, or whatever they call it, which they will have to be the Righteouſneſs by which we are Juſtified, is not of Grace neither: It is not the Gift of God, he never purpoſed or promiſed to give it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any: It is not the Purchaſe of Chriſt, he never merited it for any: It is not the Work of the Spirit of Grace, he does no more towards it in thoſe that have it, than in thoſe that never have it.</p>
               <p>So that the Righteouſneſs whereby they are Juſtified, is ſo far from being that which Chriſt performed, that he did not ſo much as Merit it; ſo far from being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60922:50"/> the Righteouſneſs of God, that he does not give it; ſo far from being the Iſſue of Gods Free Grace, that it is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our Free-will. How Sinners are Juſtified, the Apoſtle declares in the Text, and <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 7. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 34. But by this Doctrine, we are ſo far from being Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied freely by his Grace, through the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Chriſt Jeſus, that we are Juſtified without the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus; not freely, not by his Grace, but by acts of our own Free-will, paſſing for a perfect Righteouſneſs; when they are no ſuch thing, nor can upon any ground be ſo accounted.</p>
               <p>(15.) It tends to <hi>deſtroy the Covenant of Grace;</hi> to make it a Covenant without Grace, I had almoſt ſaid an ungracious Compact; ſuch, wherein the Lord ſhews himſelf leſs gracious to Men, than if they had been left under the Covenant of Works; and under which, they are more liable to Sin and Damnation, than if it had never been made: Which thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</p>
               <p>The Covenant of Works required per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Obedience; and Man, being created after the Image of God, with Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, was able to perform that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60922:50"/> perfect Obedience which was the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Covenant; but tranſgreſſing it by that firſt act of Diſobedience, in eating the forbidden Fruit, he loſt the Image of God, wherein his ſtrength for obſerving the Covenant conſiſted: The Lord, they ſay, deprived him of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs, and thereby of ability to perform the Condition. Now they ſay, a Man cannot ſin in not doing that which he is not able to perform, though he be diſabled by his own fault; and ſo in this ſtate of diſability, he was not capable of ſinning, and conſequently was not liable to Condemnation.</p>
               <p>If things had continued in this ſtate, none could have been Damned for actual Sin, but <hi>Adam</hi> only; and they ſay, for Original Sin none are Damned.</p>
               <p>But the Covenant of Grace made a ſad alteration in Mans ſtate and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for therein, ſufficient Grace being offered to all, whereby they may avoid Sin if they will; they hereupon become ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſinning, as they were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and in danger of Damnation, when before they were ſafe. So that their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace makes Mans Condition worſe than it was, inſtead of relieving
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60922:51"/> him, ſo far is it from being truly graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; even the ſuppoſed Grace of it, brings him more within the compaſs of Sin and Damnation than he was without it.</p>
               <p>(16.) It <hi>Caſhiers the Spirit of Grace,</hi> and all its ſpecial Offices and Operations. To paſs by thoſe who aſcribe nothing at all to the Spirit; thoſe who attribute moſt to it, ſo far as I can diſcern, will have us beholding to him for nothing at all, but common Light, ſuch as the Childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Darkneſs have; and ſo weak and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſs, that the Will needs not follow it is not determined, nor effectually move<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or inclined by it. The Spirit of Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (with them) has no immediate Influenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the Will or Affections; and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is all too which the Mind has from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit, it moves neither Will nor Affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but remotely, but by vertue of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Light: So that the Spirit of Grace do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing in the whole Soul, Mind, Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Affections, but what this light amoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to. No more is needful, either for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt riſe of Holineſs, or for the increaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and growth, or the ſtrengthening and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuance of it.</p>
               <p>At firſt, the Will, by no other hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than that of Moral Grace, (which pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60922:51"/> to no inward Operation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but only this common Illumination; for the Propoſal is by the Word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and the inforcing of Motives and Arguments, is by the Miniſtry of Man,) determines it ſelf to turn to God; and ſo, without more adoe, is Converted and Regenerated. There is the riſe of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; afterwards by determining it ſelf again and again, it acquires a habit, and that is a free and permanent Quality: That the Will exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b.</hi> tom. 1. p. 316.</note> increaſes, ſtrengthens and confirms Holineſs, as it began it, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining it ſelf: It has Power to do this in and of it ſelf, and nothing elſe does, or can do it. The Spirit, neither by this Light, nor by any other gracious Influence, does, or can determine it: Nor does the Will need any thing for the exerciſe of its Power, but only Light to make a ſufficient diſcovery of the Duty or Object propounded. Thus all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Operations, Aſſiſtances, of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Grace, are confined to this Light: All its healing, ſtrengthening, quickening and eſtabliſhing Vertue, amounts to no more than this: The Soul neither has, nor needs any ſpiritual Life, Health,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60922:52"/> Strength, or Motion, either firſt or laſt, but what this does effect; and yet it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects no ſuch thing in far the moſt that have it: For thoſe have it, no leſs than others, who are, in the ſtyle of Scripture, not only in the dark, but Darkneſs. And if it have any more effect upon others, than it has upon the Children of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet this efficacy it muſt have from Free-will; not of it ſelf, nor of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, (whom they call its Author,) other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would be equally effectual in all, ſince all have it equally, and the Spirit is ſuppoſed to give it equally to all. And if the Spirit of Chriſt give it not its Efficacy and Vertue, but it owes this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Free-will; it is of no worth as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> proceeds from the Spirit, of no more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue than a fruitleſs and ineffectual thing; of no Vertue, and ſo of no value, but what it derives from Mans Will.</p>
               <p>Now what Honour is it to the Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſt, to aſcribe to him a fruitleſs a worthleſs thing? They ſeem to honour the Spirit as much, who will borrow no light at all from him; but count the light of Reaſon, with the help of the written Word, ſufficient: And what great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is there betwixt them who aſcribe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60922:52"/> nothing at all to the Spirit, and thoſe that aſcribe to him that which is nothing worth? That which is fruitleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual, of no Vertue, of no Value, but but what it owes to Mans Will, may as well be aſcribed to humane Reaſon, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the divine Spirit.</p>
               <p>(17.) It tends to <hi>deſtroy the Mediation of Chriſt:</hi> That liberty, which they make eſſential to Mans Will, makes Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being the Mediator between God and Man, and ſo tends to ruine all the concerns of God and Man in Chriſts Mediation. For, either the Will of Chriſt was undeclinably fixed upon that which is Good and Holy, ſo that it could not to Diſobedience and Wickedneſs: And if ſo, it had not that indifferency to good and evil, in which they place the liberty of Mans Will, and count it eſſential there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſo that it cannot be a humane Will without it; and then Chriſt, wanting that which is eſſential to humane Nature, was not indeed a Man, nor did aſſume our Nature; conſequently could not be the Mediator between God and Man, being not the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Or, if his Will was not undeclinably fixed on that which was good, but left
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60922:53"/> in a ſtate of indifferency to that or the contrary; ſo that he might have obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Fathers Will, or not obſerved it; might have loved him, or not loved him; might hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fulfilled all righteouſneſs, or not fulfilled it: And if he might have ſinned, or not ſinned, then he was not God; for he that is God cannot ſin.</p>
               <p>So that as they ſtate the freedom of Mans Will, either he was not Man, or he was not God; and either way he could not be Mediator, who muſt be both. Thus all the advantages Sinners have by his Mediation periſh; and all the Glory the Lord deſigned to himſelf thereby, is blaſted by the extravagant Doctrine of Free-will.</p>
               <p>(18.) It <hi>defaces Redemption by Chriſt,</hi> and leaves little or no place, or no neceſſity, either of Satisfaction or Merit, in his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Sufferings.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He did not <hi>merit Faith, or Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> or <hi>Holineſs,</hi> or <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> for all, or for any particular Perſons. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare expreſly, that it is fooliſhly ſaid, that Chriſt procured Faith or Regeneration for any: Their Principles ingage them to maintain this; for if he merited theſe for any, it would have been neceſſary that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60922:53"/> theſe ſhould have been wrought in ſome of the Redeemed; it would have been ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that ſome or other of them ſhould be Believers, regenerate and ſanctified, and ſtedfaſt unto the end; but all ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity they deny, as inconſiſtent with that freedom of Mans Will which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for. It muſt not be under any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, either from the Decree of God or the Purchaſe of Chriſt: Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Sanctification, Perſeverance, muſt be meer Contingencies, in reſpect of thoſe former Cauſes; or elſe they could not be free Acts in reſpect of the Will, their next Cauſe. Chriſt, by his Death and Merit, muſt not be the Author or Cauſe of theſe, though there be no Pardon or Life without them; ſo much muſt not be aſcribed to his Merits, leſt too little be left to Free-will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Upon the ſame Account, <hi>Chriſt did not Merit Pardon</hi> or <hi>Salvation</hi> for any one certainly; and ſo his Death makes nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Means nor the End certain. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had done and ſuffered ſo much, been obedient unto Death, made his Soul an Offering for Sin, and obtained Eternal Redemption by his Blood; yet there was no Neceſſity that any one Sinner ſhould
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60922:54"/> have Pardon and Life; no Certainty, that any one would be Pardoned and Saved: Chriſt left this altogether uncertain, and not to be determined but by Mans Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. After Chriſt had finiſhed the Work of Redemption, as all might have been Saved, ſo all might have been Damned; There was no Value, Efficacy, Merit or Satisfaction, in Chriſts Death or Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to make more ſure Work: It was left at uncertainty, as it were at hap hazard, whether Salvation or Damnation ſhould carry it; and Free-will alone muſt have the honour to determine it. Chriſt, they ſay, procured<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grevincov. in Ameſ. Coron.</hi> p. 142.</note> by his Death a Power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Unbelievers: So that he no more Purchaſed Salvation than Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; he is, by Vertue of his Death and Obedience, no more a Redeemer than a Deſtroyer of Mankind: Whether he ſhould prove a Saviour of any, or a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of all, is left to the arbitrement of Free-will. There was, they ſay,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> no other Neceſſity, nor Advantage, nor Value, in the Death of Chriſt, but what might have been perfectly ſalved, though all the Redeemed had Periſhed Eternally.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60922:54"/>
               <p>They declare for an Univerſal Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that equally extended to all and every one, and ſo would ſeem to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it more than others: Yet indeed it is no other Redemption of all, but ſuch as is very well conſiſtent with the Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all and every one. Chriſt loved them all, and waſhed them from their Sins in his own Blood; yet for all that, every one of them might have been Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Though they ſay, he Died and ſhed his Blood for the whole World; yet there's no Value, Efficacy or Merit, in the Death of Chriſt, in the Blood of God, to ſecure Pardon and Salvation, or any ſaving Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to any one Perſon in the World. All might have Periſhed, for any thing he had effected by the Work of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and all had Periſhed certainly, if he had procured no more for them, than the Doctrine of Free-will can admit of; not one of them can ever come to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, if Chriſt did not procure more for them, and more effectually, than their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine will ſuffer them to acknowledge, or give him any thanks for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If he did not <hi>purchaſe Pardon and Life</hi> certainly for any, nor Faith and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, or other ſuch neceſſary requiſites
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60922:55"/> thereto, what then did he Procure? Why, he Procured, they ſay, a Covenant or Promiſe, that all ſhould have Pardon and Life, if they would Believe and Obey him.</p>
               <p>But if, antecedently to Chriſts under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, the Lord had declared his willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſave ſuch as Believe and Obey, there was no need of ſuch a Promiſe; and ſo Chriſt procured a needleſs thing, or nothing.</p>
               <p>Or, if he did not purchaſe the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Covenant, (<hi>viz.</hi> Grace to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and Obey) unleſs it was in the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their own Wills, without Chriſt, to Perform the Conditions; ſtill he Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for them as good as nothing.</p>
               <p>But if it were otherwiſe, yet thoſe who would have us to aſcribe to the Death and Obedience of Chriſt nothing but this, would not have us Obliged to aſcribe to it either Satisfaction or Merit. No Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, unleſs it be to his Fathers Will, not to his Juſtice in this ſenſe. The Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Death of Chriſt was ſo fully ſatisfying, ſo very acceptable to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Will, he was ſo well pleaſed with it, that hereupon he entred into this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. There was no need of other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60922:55"/> than this; it was enough, if he did Merit it; ſufficient, if his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did deſerve ſuch a Promiſe for us.</p>
               <p>Nay, there was no need of Merit: For, as the Lord was ſo well pleaſed with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Faith and Obedience, as for his ſake he vouchſafed his Poſterity many Favours, though the Patriarch did not merit ſo much; ſo the Lord might be ſo well pleaſed with the Obedience and Sufferings of Chriſt, as for his ſake to make ſuch a Promiſe, without any Merit obliging him to it. Thus way is made, to ſtrip Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption both of Satisfaction and Merit, without which it is, it can be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption indeed; the Name may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but the Thing denyed; all neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, and all advantage by it too, but what is left to the arbitrement of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.</p>
               <p>(19.) It is <hi>inconſiſtent with the Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Attributes of God;</hi> with his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Power, Wiſdom, Truth and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, with his Soveraignty and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World, and other Divine Excellencies. But, that I may not ſtay too long on this Subject, let me inſiſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on theſe mentioned.</p>
               <p>1. It <hi>Defaces the Mercy</hi> of God, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60922:56"/> makes it in effect no Mercy. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend indeed to repreſent God under ſuch a Notion as will indear him, and render him lovely to the World, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Mercy and Goodneſs, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſiveneſs and Univerſality; but when their Pretenſions are ſtrictly and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally examined, they prove quite of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tendency: That Mercy which they aſcribe to God, is without an Object, or without Effect, or without Grace; a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which is not an Honour to him, nor an Indearment of him to others.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a <hi>Mercy without an Object;</hi> a Mercy not for any certain Perſon, but for Qualities, which are no Objects of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: A Mercy for ſome, when it appears not who they are, or whether there will be any ſuch. A Mercy for no Body, which pretends to be for all and every one, when it is not for any one. This is their antecedent Mercy, whereby they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that he loves all that Believe and Obey, before he knows who they are, and is uncertain whether ever any ſuch will be. It ſpeaks a reſpect to thoſe Qualities, but no Love or good Will for any particular Perſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a <hi>Mercy without Effect:</hi> They
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60922:56"/> aſcribe to him a Will of Univerſal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; when they diſcern it can be no other than a meer Velleity, an incompleat Intention, a weak ineffectual Deſire, a faint and fruitleſs Wiſhing of ſuch gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Happineſs, when he knows it will never be effected, and is reſolved not to take the courſe to effect it. This is ſuch a Mercy, as juſtles out and claſhes with his other Perfections, and is inconſiſtent with his Knowledge, Power, Sincerity, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Bleſſedneſs, and Mercy it ſelf in the true Notion of it.</p>
               <p>With his Knowledge; for who will deſire and deſign that, which he knows will never be effected? With his Power; for who will not effect that, which he really intends and deſigns, if he be able? With his Sincerity; for what Ingenuous Perſon will pretend to deſire and deſign that which he never means to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout? With his Wiſdom; for who will Propoſe to himſelf an End, and never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Means, which are proper, and alone ſufficient to obtain it? With his Bleſſedneſs; for to fall ſhort continually of what one deſires and intends, is an Unhappineſs: With the Nature of Divine Mercy and Goodneſs; for that is not real
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60922:57"/> goodneſs, which does no good, or not the good it makes ſhew of. That is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mercy indeed, which leaves the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of it miſerable, when it can relieve them; that wiſhes them well, but lets them periſh eternally. But that which they aſcribe to God, is ſuch a Mercy, as can well digeſt the everlaſting Miſery of all Mankind: Such a Love, ſuch a Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as could be ſatisfied, if not one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World ſhould be Saved.</p>
               <p>They decry the Doctrine of their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, as that which <hi>ſtraitens the Mercy of God,</hi> and confines it <hi>to a few;</hi> whereas indeed it makes Salvation ſure to very many. But by their Principles, for any Mercy there is in God, all Men may be Damned; nay, which is more, no Man can be Saved. By all the Mercy they aſcribe to God, no Man can eſcape Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; all being left to the arbitrement and indifferency of Mans corrupt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Will; which, without other help than Mercy in their way provides, will certainly ruine them Eternally. Mercy, they ſay, will Save all that Believe, and none elſe: But this Mercy intends not to work ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith in any; there is no Decree for that, it muſt be left to Mans Will; and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60922:57"/> if that be not better to him herein than the Mercy of God, he muſt unavoidably periſh. All muſt be Damned, unleſs Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will help them by its own Power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any effectual Aſſiſtance that Mercy prepared for them from Eternity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a <hi>Mercy without Grace:</hi> A Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which is not free and gracious, which will not expreſs it ſelf to any, but ſuch as are Worthy, ſuch as have ſome Merit, or ſome Motive to Oblige him to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful. And being a Mercy that is not free and gracious, whatever Mercy of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they aſcribe to him, we can never be ſaved by Grace.</p>
               <p>Nay, ſince it is not Grace, it is not Mercy indeed; no Mercy that the Lord will own, or Sinners can have any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by: It is Affection of their own, not that Divine Excellency which he glories in, and glorifies upon loſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: For that which ſaves Sinners is free Mercy, and free Mercy is nothing but Grace. So that if we be ſaved without Grace, we are ſaved without Mercy too, that which is ſo indeed; and if they have no Salvation for Sinners, but that which is without Grace and free Mercy, they leave them none at all.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60922:58"/>
               <p>That they admit of no free Mercy, no Grace in God for Sinners, appears, in that they make his firſt Purpoſe of Love (the Decree, which comprizes all the Mercy he had from Eternity for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons) to have its riſe from Faith or Works foreſeen. He foreſees, that when it is left to the Free-will, to the choice of all; theſe will of themſelves, without Divine determining Power, Believe and Love him; others will not; and therefore he will Love, and purpoſes to Save theſe, and not others: And ſo he loves them not freely, but becauſe they Oblige him: He Loves them, <hi>i. e.</hi> He Purpoſes to Save them, becauſe they Love him firſt. Thus that which God foreſees in Man, is the Condition of the Mercy and Favour he intends; and ſuch a Condition, as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Cauſe, the Motive, and in the ancient ſenſe of the Word, the Merit of his Favour and Mercy: And ſo they leave no free Mercy in God for Sinners; and Sinners being capable of no Mercy at all, but what is free, they leave in him no Mercy at all for them. This is, in the Apoſtles ſenſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 4. to <hi>fall from Grace,</hi> to deny, to renounce all Grace, all free Mercy of God which the Goſpel diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60922:58"/> The Doctrine of Free-will obliges them to diſclaim all the Mercy of God, by which any Sinner can be ſaved.</p>
               <p>2. This <hi>deſtroys the Preſcience of God:</hi> Though they be concerned to maintain this, as well as we, and pretend to do it; yet their Doctrine is utterly inconſiſtent with it, and makes it impoſſible for him to foreknow certainly any thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon Mans Will: And ſo bereaves him of the certain foreknowledge of thoſe things, which are of greateſt moment and conſequence, both to God and Man. For example.</p>
               <p>He cannot certainly foreſee, whether any will have the Goſpel; the Preaching of it depends on Mans Will. And ſo, whether any will uſe the Light of Nature well; whether any will have moral Grace, any rational Advice or Excitement by the Word: Nor whether any will Repent and Believe, whether any will be Juſtified or Sanctified, whether any will Perſevere to the end, whether any one will be Saved, nor whether any would be Redeemed; whether Chriſt would be put to Death, or any thing elſe, to which the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Mans Will is neceſſary. This is plain, becauſe by their Principles, the Will
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60922:59"/> of Man is always indifferent to act or not to act; and ſo before, and until it act, it cannot but be uncertain whether it will act or not: (Nothing can make it certain, no Decree, no Act of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſtroying its liberty;) And being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, it cannot be certainly foreknown.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100-151" type="pages">
               <p>All that ever I could hear in Anſwer to this, was only, that Gods Knowledge is Infinite: And though we cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, how that which is uncertain can be certainly known; yet an Infinite Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding can reach it, and have the certain Knowledge of that which is Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain.</p>
               <p>But this makes it more evidently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible: For the more perfect any Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is, the farther it is from Error and Miſtake. So Infinite Knowledge muſt be fartheſt of all from erring; but to know that as certain, which is not certain, is not to Know, but to Err; not to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend things as they are, but to miſtake and miſapprehend them, to have falſe and erroneous apprehenſions of them. As they ſtate the Freedom of the Will, God can have no certain foreknowledge of thoſe things, without falſe and erroneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions thereof. They leave him nothing
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60922:59"/> here but Conjectures, or nothing but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes and Error.</p>
               <p>3. It Impeaches the <hi>Truth and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> of God; overthrows the Truth and Certainty of his Word, in all the parts of it; leaves no certainty of his Truth and Faithfulneſs in Prophecies, Promiſes, Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Aſſertions, contained in Scripture. It cannot be certain, by their Principles, that the Prophecies will be accompliſhed, the Promiſes fulfilled, or the Threatnings executed; and ſo it muſt be uncertain, whether they are true or falſe: There is no certainty that they will prove true, they may as well prove falſe. The ſame muſt be ſaid of many Aſſertions too; there is no Neceſſity, no Certainty, that they will prove true, <hi>v. g. Can. 1. 4. Jer. 31. 18. Lam.</hi> 5. 21.</p>
               <p>By this Doctrine, there can be no <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> that <hi>they will turn,</hi> whatever Courſe the Lord take to turn them; or that they <hi>will run after him,</hi> what Courſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he take to draw them: And ſo thoſe Aſſertions are not Neceſſarily true, but may prove falſe; and ſo may thoſe, and the like to thoſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 33, 34. This is manifeſt alſo in thoſe Predictions and Promiſes, where the Concurrence of Mans
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60922:60"/> Will is requiſite: For as they ſtate its Freedom, there can be no <hi>Certainty,</hi> which way it will incline and determine it ſelf, whether with the Word, and according to the tenor of the Prediction, or againſt it. Nor will they allow, that God can make ſure of it, or take any Courſe that will ſo determine it, that the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Word ſhall not be defeated. For when he has done what he can to incline it that way which his Word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that it may prove true; yet it is, and muſt be left free to incline the other way, and make his Word prove falſe. Let us clear this by ſome inſtances, in each of thoſe parts of the Word, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God is (if any where) eminently concerned. There is an ancient Prophecy, of the <hi>Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Gentiles,</hi> Gen. 9. 27. <hi>God ſhall perſwade Japhet,</hi> i. e. the Gentiles who deſcended from him, and they ſhall <hi>joyn themſelves to the People of God.</hi> Now by the Doctrine of Free-will, the Lord is to do nothing that can make it certain, that <hi>Japhet</hi>'s Poſterity ſhall comply herewith: He is only to Propoſe it to them by the Preaching of the Goſpel, and leave thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wills in an Indifferency, to yield hereto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60922:60"/> or not to yield. So that it muſt be a meer Contingency, whether this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy would be accompliſhed or no, if it might prove true, ſo it might prove falſe. The ſame may be ſaid of thoſe Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Joh. 10. 16. Act. 28. 28. Joh.</hi> 12. 32. The Truth and Faithfulneſs of God in theſe and other Prophecies is evidently expoſed, paſt all ſecurity their Principles can poſſibly give.</p>
               <p>So it is likewiſe in the <hi>Promiſes</hi> and the Covenant of Grace, ſtyled <hi>Everlaſting;</hi> everlaſting Truth and Faithfulneſs being ingaged for the Performance of it, <hi>Jer. 32. 39, 40. Ezek.</hi> 36. 26, 27. Every Clauſe of this may prove falſe, and not be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled to any one Perſon in the World: For, with them, the Lord does nothing which will certainly change the Hearts of Men, but only offers Arguments to move them to renew their own Hearts; and ſo leaves it to the arbitrement of their own Wills, whether ever the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhall take effect or not. Now, if it were poſſible, that it ſhould prove true, that Man ſhould make himſelf a New Heart; yet it is more likely that it ſhould prove falſe, becauſe Mans corrupt Will, to which it is left, is more inclined to make
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60922:61"/> it falſe than true. Take it at the beſt, to make the Truth of God in the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant to depend on Mans Will, ſuppoſing it indifferent, is bad enough: For if it be indifferent whether God ſhall be True or no, it muſt be indifferent whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be God or no.</p>
               <p>Thus it will be, not only as to the Promiſes made <hi>to us,</hi> but alſo thoſe which are made <hi>to Chriſt,</hi> Iſa. 49. 6, 7. &amp; 53. 10. &amp; 55. 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 8. &amp; 72. 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 5, 6. Theſe and the like may all prove falſe: Mans Will, to which it is left, may ſo carry it, and this unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that not one of them ſhall be made good. Nor will they allow the Lord to take any courſe with Mans Will, or have any ſuch influence on it, as will be ſure to prevent this, or make it any way cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that his Truth herein ſhall not fail: He muſt not determine the Will that way which is neceſſary to ſecure his Truth in performing his Promiſes. Nor in the Threatning neither, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 16, 17. Whatever be ſaid of Gods <hi>putting it into their Hearts;</hi> yet they will not have us imagine, that the Lord will effectually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine their Wills to this; but theſe muſt be left free and indifferent, either
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60922:61"/> to Love or Hate the Whore; either to do what is foretold, or not to do it; to make it true, or to make it falſe.</p>
               <p>Now if theſe parts of the Word of God may prove falſe, or if they be not certainly true, all the reſt will be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Truth and Certainty of all the Scripture is overthrown: If the Truth or Faithfulneſs of God may fail us here, where can we be ſure of it? The glory of this Divine Perfection is uttetly defaced. The Truth and Faithfulneſs of God is the ground of all Divine Faith. We believe God, becauſe he is infallibly True, and what he ſays cannot prove falſe: But it may prove falſe by their Doctrine, and ſo the ground of all Chriſtian, of all Divine Faith is quite razed, and the Foundation of all Religion is hereby undermined, yea quite blown up.</p>
               <p>4. It <hi>deſtroys the Government of God,</hi> as to the greateſt Concerns of the World. By their Hypotheſis, the Will of Man is not, cannot be ruled by him: He muſt not touch it immediately; it is a thing ſo Sacred, that a touch, even of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may violate it. He muſt not Inſpire it with any new Quality, nor Move it by any real Influence, but only make his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60922:62"/> to it at a diſtance, by propoſing an Object, and offering Motives and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: And if this will not do, (as it does not, nor alone ever can do, in the Concerns of Salvation,) he muſt leave it to it ſelf, to do what it liſt. Now that which is left to do as it liſt, is not Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it is not under Government.</p>
               <p>They will have the Lord to treat it as an Orator, not as a Soveraign Ruler. The Will (with them) ſeems to have a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty exempted from the Soveraignty of God; not ſubordinate to it, if not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it; not ſubjected to the Soveraign Government of God, further than to do what it liſt.</p>
               <p>Hereby God is excluded from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World. Men are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by their Wills, that is the Ruling, the Commanding Faculty; therefore if the Will be not under his Government, Men will not be under it, nor the reſt of the World, ſo far as it is governed by Men. If he Diſpoſe not of that which orders the reſt, what is there left at his Diſpoſal? All the Affairs of the World, which depend upon humane Conduct, will be governed more by the Will of Man, than by the Will, Power, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60922:62"/> of God: By the Will of Man independently, as if he were God; but by the Lord of Heaven and Earth only Precariouſly, and at the Pleaſure of Mans Will, as if he were a Subject, an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, an inferior Creature.</p>
               <p>5. It denyes the <hi>Almighty Power of God,</hi> will not admit him to be Omnipotent, and his Power Infinite: It is not Infinite, if it be bounded and limited; yet Mans Will bounds and limits the Divine Power. By their Principles, the Lord can no way deal with the Will, but ſo that it may reſiſt him, and render all his Actings and Operations on it ineffectual: He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail with it in any thing ſo far, but that it may at once ſtand out and repell his Motions, render every Divine Attempt upon it ſucceſleſs: When he has done all that can be done by the Power of his Grace, the Will may be too hard for him; it muſt be always left to do what it liſt. He cannot Save a Man, how much ſoever he intends or deſires it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be the Wills Pleaſure: Nor can he take any Courſe to make the Will plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with it. He can neither ſo Change the Faculty, nor ſo repreſent the Object, but the Will may ſtill reject it. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60922:63"/> work Faith in him, nor bring him to Repentance, nor Create Holineſs in his Heart; nor can he Continue him in a ſtate of Holineſs, unleſs it pleaſe the Will to ſubmit; nor can he bring it to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo, but that it may refuſe, when all is done that his Grace can do. He can make no particular Decrees concerning Man, that are Poſitive and Peremptory, becauſe he cannot maſter Mans Will: His Purpoſes muſt be Conditional and Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Free-will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He cannot make good his own Word, not verifie what he Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, nor accompliſh his own Prophecies, nor perform his Promiſes, if Mans Will ſtand in his way: Nor can he clear his way of it in any Method, but what the Will of Man may defeat. He cannot Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his Deſires and Intentions, if Mans Will reſiſt him, and can never put the Will out of a Capacity of reſiſting and oppoſing, while it is a Will. It is eſſential to the Will, to be always able to reſiſt; and if they ſtand not to this, they yield all: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135. 6. No, muſt they ſay, there are innumerable which God cannot do, unleſs Man pleaſes: <hi>Phil. 3. ult.</hi> Chriſt has a Power, whereby he <hi>can ſubdue all things,</hi> &amp;c. No, muſt they
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60922:63"/> ſay, the things wherein he is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned of all other in this World, the Wills of Men, he cannot ſubdue to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 1. No, muſt they ſay, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Hearts of Kings,</hi> nor of any other Men, are thus <hi>in the Lords hands:</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he does to turn the Current of them, they may run in the old Channel, and keep their own Courſe for all that: It is not whitherſoever he will that they turn, but whitherſoever they will, they run, for all his turning.</p>
               <p>(20.) It <hi>Idolizes Mans Will,</hi> makes it in divers reſpects equal with, or above him.</p>
               <p>It ſeems to <hi>ſubject God,</hi> and make him an Underling to Mans Will; and that in reſpect of his Will, his Word, his Grace, his Deſign. Some of theſe are apparent by what is already ſaid: Let me only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on one particular. It makes God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant on the Will of Man, even for his Glory; where it is moſt intolerable for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Majeſty of Heaven to be depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and moſt inconſiſtent with his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Perfection and Happineſs. The Lord in all the Operations of his Grace, leaves the Will indifferent either to comply or reſiſt. This leaves it to the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60922:64"/> and Arbitrement of Mans Will, whether God ſhall have the Glory of that, by which he deſigns to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt glorious. It muſt be in the Power of Mans Will to defeat God there, where he intends moſt of all to glorifie himſelf; to ſpoil and deface the glory of his Grace and Love, where the Riches thereof are moſt diſplayed: And this in the greateſt and moſt ſignal Inſtances of it, and where each Perſon in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head are moſt eminently concerned.</p>
               <p>Whatever Decree or Purpoſe of Love and Grace the Lord had from Eternity, to Save loſt Sinners, it muſt be at the Determination of Mans Will, whether any one ſhall be ſaved or freed from Miſery. After the Work of Redemption finiſhed by Chriſt, it muſt be at the Pleaſure of Mans Will, whether any one ſhall be actually Redeemed. After the Spirit of Grace has done what can be done, for changing the Hearts, and renewing the Natures of Sinners; yet not one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>Scan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them ſhall be Changed or Sanctified, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſs they liſt.</p>
               <p>So that, unleſs Man will, when he is left indifferent, to will or not to will, electing Grace, redeeming Grace, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60922:64"/> Grace, ſhall be of no effect, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver arrive at what it tends to. And if it be rendered of none effect, it is rendered inglorious, it is defeated, defaced, and the glory of it turned into ſhame. But ſo it muſt be, if Man will; all the Grace of God muſt be in vain, and all the Glory of it vaniſh.</p>
               <p>Thus is God evidently made <hi>dependant on Mans Will,</hi> even for his Glory, that of his Grace; and he will as ſoon be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the Will of Man in any thing, in all things, as the greateſt Concerns of his Glory.</p>
               <p>The Grace of God, where it ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in its greateſt luſtre, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the greateſt Honour of Father, Son, and Spirit; muſt wait as a Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid on Mans degenerate Will, and be ordered at its Arbitrement, and ſtand to its Pleaſure, whether it ſhall come to any thing or nothing; whether it ſhall have any Glory or none.</p>
               <p>Let them believe it who can, I can never believe that the Doctrine is of God, which offers ſuch an intolerable Indignity to him: If there were no other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it, this ſeems enough to me. The</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60922:65"/>IV. Fourth Head I propounded, was to give an account of the <hi>Objections</hi> they make, and the <hi>Prejudices</hi> they have againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Grace;</hi> and to ſhew, the worſt they can Object againſt it is as chargeable upon the Doctrine of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. So that their imbracing it ſeems to proceed from neglect of Impartial Conſideration, and ſome want of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Reaſon which they ſo much magnifie. That uſes not to be counted a rational and conſiderate Invention, which ſerves not the turn for which it was deviſed, but runs them into the ſame difficulties which they ſeek to avoid. Let us ſee briefly in two or three of the chief Inſtances, whether this be not the Caſe here.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They Charge us with <hi>making God the Author of Sin: (Tilenus</hi> ſays this was the Reaſon that turned him off to the <hi>Remonſtrants.</hi>) We diſclaim and abhorr it, and Condemn thoſe who aſſert any ſuch thing. They ſay, it is the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of our Doctrine, which will have things ſo ordered by the Decrees and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, that Sin is thereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable. We ſay, if God be made the Author of Sin on this account, their own
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60922:65"/> Doctrine is to be charged with making him ſo, by as good Conſequence. And ſo they muſt acknowledge that they wrong us, or elſe condemn themſelves and their own Principles.</p>
               <p>That they are as liable to this Charge, if it be juſt, does thus appear. He that puts Men in thoſe Circumſtances, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he foreſees that they will certainly ſin, orders things ſo, that Sin becomes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable: But by their Doctrine, the Lord decrees to place Men, and by his Providence diſpoſes them in thoſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, wherein he foreſees they will certainly ſin; <hi>e. g.</hi> The Lord foreſaw, that if <hi>Adam</hi> was Created ſo and ſo, and ſet in ſuch Circumſtances, he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Sin and Fall by it: Yet foreſeeing this, the Lord decreed to Create him ſo, and diſpoſe of him in ſuch Circumſtances, and actually did it. He foreſees, that if <hi>Peter</hi> be put in thoſe Circumſtances where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was found in the High-Prieſt's Hall, he would certainly deny his Maſter: But he Decreed thus to diſpoſe of him, and by his Providence actually did it. This is the plain Import of their Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Conditional Foreknowledge in God, as will be evident to any that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60922:66"/> it. It was an Invention of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> the laſt Age, to make good their Doctrine of Free-will and Moral Grace, and to avoid the ſuppoſed Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the oppoſite Doctrine; and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly imbraced by thoſe who agree with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in their Opinion about the Power of the Will: But a very impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and unhappy Device it was, ſince it involves them in thoſe very Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which it was deviſed to avoid.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They charge our Doctrine, as <hi>make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God unmerciful,</hi> becauſe he gives not to the greateſt part of Mankind, that Grace which is neceſſary to Salvation: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we deny not that God gives that Grace which they count ſufficient; we grant he gives all that Grace which is neceſſary by their Doctrine, even to Reprobates. But we ſay, their Doctrine, how much ſoever it triumphs in advancing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Gods Love to Mankind; yet it makes him far more unmerciful, in that it will not have God to vouchſafe that Grace which is neceſſary or ſufficient for Salvation, ſpecial Grace, to any at all. Meer ſwaſive Grace, which leaves it to the choice of Mans unrenewed Will, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will turn to God or no, which
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60922:66"/> they ſay is all that God vouchſafes to any, did never alone, can never of it ſelf Save any Man: And ſo they will have, not only ſome, but all Men to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, for any Grace that God gives them. Whatever Oſtentation it makes of magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Divine Mercy, yet what Doctrine can be more unmerciful, than that which leaves all Men to be Damned, unleſs their Free-will do ſomething more for them than the Grace of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They ſay, we <hi>Impeach the Sincerity of God,</hi> when he by his Word calls ſuch as Periſh to Repentance, that they may be Saved; and yet has Decreed no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to give them Repentance, but to Damn them: So that it is certain, (while thoſe Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Offers are made in the Word) that they ſhall not Repent and be Saved. This, they ſay, makes the Word and the Miniſtry of it Deluſive, and no better than Simulation, making ſhow of that to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which is never intended, and which it is impoſſible they ſhould have.</p>
               <p>The ground of this Charge, is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that ſuch ſhall never Repent and be Saved: But their own Principles make this no leſs certain: For they ſay, God foreſees from Eternity that ſuch will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60922:67"/> Repent, and ſo ſhall never be Saved: And what he foreſees (his Foreknowledge being Certain and Infallible) will as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come to paſs, and is as impoſſible not to be, as that which he Decrees. Nay, they ſay, that the Lord, upon his Foreknowledge that ſuch would not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, did Decree from Eternity to Damn them, and never Decreed to give them Repentance, nor any Grace or Aid that would effectually bring them to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; no, nor any, but what he certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreſaw would be ineffectual. So that here alſo they muſt either Juſtifie our Doctrine, as to this Charge, or Condemn their own.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They ſay, our Doctrine <hi>makes God <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt and Cruel,</hi> in Exacting that from Men which they are not able to do; and Condemning them for not doing that which he gives them not ſtrength to do <hi>v. g.</hi> for requiring Sinners to Believe and Turn to God, and Condemning them for not complying with him herein; when he knows they cannot do it of themſelves and when he gives them no Grace to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them for it. They make large Harangues on this Subject, tending to render their Oppoſites odious; and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60922:67"/> them off with ſuch Similitudes and Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations as make Impreſſion on weak Minds, which are more apt to be taken with Words, than to weigh and conſider things. Whereas after all, the plain truth is, there is no Doctrine that I know of more chargeable with this, than their own. For it is very evident in Scripture, and in the Nature of the thing, that their ſwaſive Grace does not give Sinners ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Power to Believe and Turn to God; it cannot ſubdue the Corruption of the Heart oppoſing this: It pretends not to give any new ſpiritual Principle of Life or Strength for theſe effects; it leaves the Will in its natural Impotency and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, to do as it liſt. And therefore, ſince, by their Doctrine, he gives Sinners no more Power but this, and yet requires them to Believe and Turn to Chriſt, and Condemns them for not doing it; he Condemns them for want of that which he gives not ſufficient Power to do.</p>
               <p>Can any one imagine, who will not offer plain Violence to a multitude of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in Scripture, that meer Moral Swaſion, which does not ſo much as move the Will out of its indifferent Poſture, can Quicken thoſe that are dead in Sins
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60922:68"/> and Treſpaſſes? can take away the Heart of Stone, and give Hearts of Fleſh; or write his Laws in them; or make thoſe Hearts that are deſperately wicked, to become holy and heavenly? Can form new Creatures of the old Man, and make old things paſs away, and all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new? Can give Strength and Life to thoſe who can do nothing, are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Strength and Life?</p>
               <p>He that cannot believe this, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to an hundred of ſuch Paſſages in the Word of God, muſt believe that their Doctrine, concerning Free-will and Moral Grace, makes God to Condemn more than any, for not doing that which he gives them not Power to do.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They ſay, <hi>We deſtroy the Liberty of the Will,</hi> by bringing it under a neceſſity of inclining one way, and not leaving it indifferent to incline the other, or to ſuſpend its Acts, <hi>e. g.</hi> When God intends to Convert a Sinner, and puts forth the Power of his Grace for this purpoſe, it is neceſſary that the Will incline no other way than his Grace moves it.</p>
               <p>But if this deſtroy the Liberty of the Will, their <hi>own Doctrine overthrows it:</hi> For they Teach, that God, from Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60922:68"/> before any Act of his Will, foreſaw which way every Mans Will, in ſuch and ſuch Circumſtances, would incline. He foreknows certainly and infallibly, that in thoſe Circumſtances it will incline this way, and not the other. Now if he know that certainly, it muſt be Certain and of Neceſſity: For to know that as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, which is not certain, is not to know but to miſtake, to apprehend a thing otherwiſe than it is. And if the Will might or could incline otherwiſe than he foreſaw, his Foreknowledge would not be Infallible: For that excludes, not only actual Error, but a poſſibility of it.</p>
               <p>If then it be true from Eternity, that the Will muſt incline this one way, it is not indifferent to incline that way or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and ſo its indifferency, its freedom from a neceſſity to incline but this one way, is gone by their own Principles. They muſt either grant, that the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Mans Will is conſiſtent with a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of inclining one way and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or yield that their own Doctrine deſtroys its liberty.</p>
               <p>Whether they will be ſo ingenuous or no, it is very certain that ſome Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may very well conſiſt with Liberty in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60922:69"/> the freeſt Agents. God is Neceſſarily good, and yet Freely: So are the Saints and Angels in Heaven; they cannot but be Holy, and act holily, yet they are ſo, and do ſo freely. The Devils and Damned in Hell are neceſſarily Wicked, they cannot be other; and yet they are ſo, and act Wickedneſs freely: Wicked men on Earth, that are habitually and judicially harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Wickedneſs, they are neceſſarily evil, and cannot but ſin, and yet they ſin free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. So that this Conceit, though it be a fundamental Doctrine with them, and the main weight of their Cauſe lyes on it, that Liberty is inconſiſtent with Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; is againſt the ſenſe, reaſon and experience of Heaven, and Earth, and Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If Salvation be of Grace, it muſt be a free Gift, offered and given freely: But we ſee in Scripture (and the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſaving Mercy make it plain) that it is offered, and ſo given upon Terms and Conditions required of thoſe that will be Saved. The Promiſes are many of of them expreſly Conditional; and ſo will the Covenant of Grace be, of which the Promiſes are but ſeveral Articles. Now that which is not Given or Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60922:69"/> but upon Terms and Conditions, ſeems not to be given or offered freely; the more Conditional, the leſs Free and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Offers of Salvation, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of ſaving Mercies, notwithſtanding any Conditionalneſs in them, any Terms annexed, are free and gracious, upon a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold account: for in many caſes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or Terms do not hinder a Grant or Promiſe from being free.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the Condition be ſo only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>outward Form</hi> and Manner of Propoſal, not properly and really: For then it ſeems to be a Condition, but is not ſtrictly. So here: Goſpel Promiſes are Conditional <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>quoad externam formam &amp; modum proponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> not <hi>propriè &amp; quoad rigorem:</hi> as to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of propoſal they ſeem Conditional; but examin them by the Laws of Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and they will be found rather Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute. If the denomination muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>à majori,</hi> or <hi>à potiori,</hi> if the Number or Weight will carry it, bring them to the Teſt, examin why they ſhould be counted Conditional or Abſolute; and it will be found, that in more reſpects, and for more weighty Conſiderations they ought
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60922:70"/> to paſs for Abſolute, rather than Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, in the <hi>Pelagian</hi> ſenſe; ſo no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to queſtion their Freeneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Condition</hi> be <hi>our Duty.</hi> If ſuch, as when we perform it we do nothing but what we owe, and the Promiſer owes nothing to us for doing it; then, if he promiſe any thing, he promiſes freely. It is <hi>promiſſio indebita pro opere debito,</hi> that is <hi>gratuita.</hi> That which is not <hi>ex debito</hi> is <hi>gratuito.</hi> Theſe are oppoſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 4. That which is no way due, if promiſed, is freely promiſed. Now all that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, is our Duty, we owe it; and for all that we can doe, God owes us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Debitum non redit in Deum: Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium non eſt divini juris naturalis;</hi> his Nature engages him not to reward his Creatures. That which he does this way is of free Will. <hi>Deus ad praemium nemini eſt obligatus. Rom.</hi> 11. 35. Eternal Life had not been due to <hi>Adam,</hi> if he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed perfect Obedience; it was only the Promiſe intitled him to it. If not due to him, much leſs to us; he might vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe no more Reward to us than to the inferiour Creatures. And ſince nothing is due from God, what he beſtowes or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, he does it freely. When we have
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60922:70"/> done all, we are but unprofitable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, we have but done our Duty, we can Chalenge no Reward: There is none due, therefore when he Promiſes any, he does it freely. The Condition being but our Duty, makes nothing due; no more than Reward is due to him that pays his Debts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Condition be <hi>Inconſiderable,</hi> compared with what <hi>is promiſed:</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one ſhould Promiſe his Tenant a Thouſand Pound <hi>per annum,</hi> if he will pay him a Pepper Corn; would any ſay, this Promiſe is not free, becauſe of ſuch a Condition? Whatever the Lord requires of us, is no more than this, compared with what he Promiſes to us. Believing and active Obeying is not ſo much as Suffering; yet if the Lord ſhould have made Sufferings the Conditions of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, they would have been free in this reſpect: Becauſe the greateſt Sufferings (ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and thoſe in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times) would be ſmall and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, compared with the Glory Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Rom. 8. 18. 2 Cor.</hi> 4. 17. Now if the hardeſt Conditions be ſo inconſiderable, what are the ſmalleſt? even nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with what is Promiſed, Grace, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, God himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:60922:71"/>4. If the Condition be not ſo much for the <hi>Advantage of the Promiſer,</hi> as to make us capable of the thing Promiſed. That which is not ſo much for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Promiſer, as for his to whom the Promiſe is made, muſt needs be from free bounty; the Promiſer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in more reſpecting the good of another, than his own: What can be more of Grace? Or if the Favour promiſed be not feiſable, without that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as a Condition of the Propoſal: If it be neceſſary to make Capable of that which is Promiſed, then it is rather a Direction how the Favour may be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than a ſtrict Condition. It does no way Prejudice the freedom of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, but rather renders it more Free and Gracious. But ſuch are many of thoſe things, which the Lord preſcribes as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, they are more for our Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage than his; he expects, he gets little or nothing by our Performance of them, <hi>Pſal. 16. 2. Job. 22. 2. Job</hi> 35. 7, 8. What Advantage has the Lord by our Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Senſe of our loſt Condition, Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the burden of Sin, Hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Thirſtings after Righteouſneſs? Why then does he annex theſe to the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60922:71"/> Promiſes; but becauſe without them we are not capable of thoſe Mercies which he is willing to beſtow? Chriſt comes to ſeek and Save what was loſt, <hi>Mat. 18. 11. Luk.</hi> 19. 10. Why is this Condition add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? thoſe that are loſt, ſenſible of their loſt Condition; but becauſe Sinners are not capable of this Favour till then? they will not be found of Chriſt, 'till they feel themſelves loſt. Why Hunger and Thirſt before be Satisfied? <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. Becauſe the Soul is till then cloſed, ſhut up, not capable of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81. 10. How can it be filled, except firſt opened? ſo himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28. Why Labour? becauſe not till then capable of reſt. When the Lord offers a Favour, and withall ſhews how it may be attained; he deals more Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more Graciouſly, than if he ſhould barely Propound it, and leave us to our own ſelves to find out the Way and Means how it might be effected.</p>
               <p>Conditions of this Nature are ſo far from making Promiſes leſs free, as they are rendered hereby more Gracious: There is as much of Free Grace in preſcribing theſe, as in Promiſing to them, becauſe without theſe the Promiſe might be of no effect, the Favour not feiſable, the Sinner not capable of it.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:60922:72"/>5. If the Condition <hi>be eaſie,</hi> no Coſt, Charge, Trouble or Hazard attend it: He that Offers upon ſuch eaſie Terms, Offers freely. If one ſhould Promiſe to Entertain his Friend, if he will but come to him; or Viſit him, if he will but let him in; or Advance him, if he be will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or give him a Jewel that will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich him for ever, if he will but receive it; or ſupply him with all his Heart can deſire, if he will but ask it: Would any Man have the Face to ſay, ſuch Offers were not Free and Gracious? are they not as Free as Heart can deſire? If a Man might chuſe his own Terms, could he Imagine, Invent, any more Eaſie?</p>
               <p>Such are the Promiſes of the Goſpel: The Lord will <hi>Entertain</hi> Sinners, if they will but <hi>Come,</hi> Iſa. 55. 1. <hi>Eaſe,</hi> Mat. 11. <hi>Satisfie,</hi> Joh. 6. 35. Or as if it were too much for Sinners to Come to him; he will <hi>Come to them,</hi> if they but <hi>Open</hi> to him, <hi>Rev. 3. 20. Give himſelf,</hi> the Pearl of great Price, if but <hi>Receive</hi> him: <hi>Marry,</hi> if but <hi>Conſent</hi> to him, <hi>Joh. 1. 12. Mat. 22. 2, 3. Give Eternal Life,</hi> if but Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. Give all Heart can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, if but <hi>Ask</hi> it, <hi>Joh. 16. 23. Open the Treaſures</hi> of Grace and Glory, if but <hi>Knock,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60922:72"/> Mat.</hi> 7. 7. Be your Friend for ever, if but <hi>Love him,</hi> Joh. 14. 21. Bear the Weight and Burden of all your Cares, if but <hi>lay them on him,</hi> Pſal. 55. 22. <hi>Never fail</hi> you in Life or Death, if but <hi>Truſt him,</hi> Pſal. 34. 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125. 1.</p>
               <p>O! how Free are theſe Offers! how Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie theſe Terms! It would be intolerable Impudence, to deſire theſe upon any Terms more Free. Would you have Chriſt your Friend, and not Love him? Marry you without your Conſent? or take Care for you, and not Truſt him? who can be ſo unreaſonable? The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions here are of ſuch a Nature, that it is even all one as if they were abſolute: No Promiſe of this Nature can be more Free, more abſolute; for the Nature of what is Promiſed, will admit of no other Terms, they are as free as can be. Can Chriſt Come to you, if you will not let him in? or Entertain you, if not Come to him? or Give himſelf, if not receive him? Nor need you ſay, theſe are not eaſie, we cannot do them of our ſelves. Chriſt prevents this; they are eaſie, if he Concur and Aſſiſt; and he engages to aſſiſt all thoſe who have Intereſt in the Promiſes, all that Come to him.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:60922:73"/>6. If the Condition <hi>be Promiſed:</hi> He that annexes a Condition to a Promiſe, and withall Promiſes to give that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, does all one as if he Promiſed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely. Suppoſe <hi>Hiram</hi> had Promiſed <hi>Solomon</hi> Cedars to build the Temple, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Condition they were Cut down; if <hi>Hiram</hi> had alſo Promiſed to Cut them down, his former Promiſe had hereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come abſolute. Or ſuppoſe <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had Promiſed <hi>Jacob</hi> that he ſhould come and be Entertained in <hi>Egypt,</hi> upon Condition that Wagons were provided to carry him; if <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſhould alſo ſend him Wagons (as he did by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 45. 19.) it is all one, as if the former Promiſe had been abſolute.</p>
               <p>So it is here: And this is enough, if there were no more, to make this Truth evident, and to prove it unanſwerably. That which the Lord ſeems to make a Condition in one place, he Promiſes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely in another: For the Promiſes of Regeneration are abſolute: The Lord free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engages himſelf to implant all Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Graces and Holy Affections in the Soul. Now to theſe, either in habit or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, are all the Promiſes made, which we count Conditional. So that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60922:73"/> of them being abſolutely Promiſed, they are in effect abſolute; <hi>e. g.</hi> The Lord Promiſes Salvation to Perſeverance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 15. He promiſes Perſeverance to Faith, <hi>Pſal. 125. 1. 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 5. and Faith is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed abſolutely, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26. A new Heart is a believing Heart; ſo that the two former, their Conditions being Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, are abſolute. He promiſes Life to thoſe that have Chriſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. He promiſes Chriſt to thoſe that Fear him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 2. and he promiſes Fear abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 40. So wherever you find any thing annexed to a Promiſe, as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, in another place you may find it, either expreſly or implicitly Promiſed: And therefore all the Promiſes are, in this reſpect, as good as Abſolute; and if Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, no reaſon to queſtion their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>If the Terms or Conditions be ſuch, as it is not poſſible in the Nature of the thing, that the Mercy offered ſhould be effected without them; then the offers of Saving Mercies are as Free and Gracious as can be, as there is any poſſibility they ſhould be; and no more can be deſired.</p>
               <p>Let me clear this in one of thoſe Terms, which is comprehenſive of all the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60922:74"/> reſt. It is required of thoſe, who will partake of <hi>ſaving Mercies,</hi> that they <hi>leave ſin,</hi> forſake their evil ways, <hi>Prov. 28. 13. Iſa. 55. 7. 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
               <p>This is the Summe of all Conditions; and whatever is required in other Terms, is included in this, or may be reſolved into it. Now it is not poſſible, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mercies ſhould otherwiſe be had, that they ſhould be received or enjoyed but upon theſe Terms; not only becauſe the Lord would have it ſo, but becauſe the Nature of the thing does ſo require it, that it is not otherwiſe feiſible.</p>
               <p>For Sin is our Impotency: Now can we poſſibly have Strength in the inner Man, if we will not part with our Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Sin is our Deformity, that which renders our Souls loathſome and ugly in the Eye of God. Now can our Souls be made Lovely, if we will not part with that which is our Defilement and Uglineſs? Can we be made Clean, if we will not part with our Leproſie? Sin is our Enmity againſt God, therein it conſiſts; Now can we poſſibly be Reconciled, if we will not lay aſide our Enmity? Sin is the Poverty of the Soul, that which robs and ſpoils, and utterly impoveriſhes the Soul: Now can
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60922:74"/> you be made Rich, if you will not part with your Poverty? Sin is the Souls reſtraint, the Dungeon where it is impriſoned, the Bonds and Fetters wherewith it is loaden: Now is it poſſible you ſhould have Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, if you will not leave your Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and part with your Fetters? Sin is the Wound, the Mortal Diſeaſe of the Soul; and can you be healed, if you will not part with your Diſeaſe? Sin is your Miſery; can you be Happy, if not part with Miſery? Happineſs conſiſts in the Enjoyment of God; but adhering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Sin, and the Enjoyment of a Holy God, are utterly inconſiſtent: And can you be Happy without Happineſs, or by retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is inconſiſtent with it?</p>
               <p>So that you ſee, there is an utter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility that Salvation ſhould be had, but upon theſe Terms: There is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency, a plain Contradiction, in any other Suppoſition. It is an Impoſſibility, not only to us, but to the Almighty; and therefore the Terms are as free and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as poſſibly could be; Omnipotent Grace it ſelf could not make them more gracious.</p>
               <p>To clear this, ſeveral things are to be obſerved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:60922:75"/>(1.) The firſt Bleſſings of the Covenant are <hi>Promiſed abſolutely;</hi> Effectual Calling, Faith, Repentance, Converſion, Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are Offered, are Promiſed without any Conditions. The Promiſes of theſe Mercies are abſolute, <hi>Ezek. 36. 26. Jer.</hi> 32. 39, 40. Under the Notions of a <hi>New Heart, a New Spirit,</hi> putting <hi>his Spirit, his Fear</hi> within them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Bleſſings fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, called the firſt Grace, are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed abſolutely; and ſo are the ſame things in other terms, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 31, 32, 33. repeated by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 8. There can be no Inſtance given in Scripture, where theſe things are Promiſed upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Indeed if they were promiſed upon Condition, Grace would be Promiſed to ſomething Natural: For this being the firſt Grace, there can be nothing before it to be the Condition of it, but what is Natural; and to make that which is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural the Condition of Grace, is groſs <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianiſm.</hi> If there were any Conditions of thoſe firſt gracious Favours, they muſt be thoſe things, which are Previous to, and Preparations for them, <hi>viz.</hi> Diligent Attendance on the Word and Means of Grace, Convictions of Sin, legal Sorrow
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60922:75"/> for it, Senſe of Wrath and Miſery, which often go before Converſion, and are count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſpoſitions or Preparations for Faith. But theſe previous Works are not Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Converſion, or the other Bleſſings included therein, nor are they promiſed upon ſuch Terms: For the Condition is never ſeparated from the Favour promiſed to it; where the Condition is performed, the Promiſe is always accompliſhed: But theſe preparatory Acts have been in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who were never truly Converted and Regenerated, never had a New Heart and a New Spirit given them: So that theſe Preparations are no Conditions of Faith or Regeneration; much leſs is there any thing of congruous Merit in them. Our Divines, that inſiſt on ſuch Preparations for Chriſt, decryed the Conceit of Merit, though in the loweſt form. This Merit of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts inferrs a Dueneſs of the thing ſo deſerved; a Dueneſs in Congruity, thô not in Juſtice: And what is due from the Lord any way, he will infallibly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow: But there may be theſe previous Diſpoſitions, where Faith is never given. There is not ſo much as a Conditional Connexion between ſuch Preparations and thoſe Bleſſings; they are Promiſed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60922:76"/> without any Condition expreſſed or implied.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The ſubſequent Bleſſings of the Covenant, thoſe that follow the firſt, are in ſome ſenſe <hi>Conditional,</hi> and ſo Offered and Promiſed in <hi>a Conditional Form,</hi> and yet are never the leſs Gracious. There are Terms and Conditions, taking the word Conditions in a latitude, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Qualifications, Adjuncts, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Antecedents, which do no way derogate from Grace; neither detract from its Freeneſs, nor obſcure, but rather illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it, <hi>Rom. 10. 8, 9, 10. Rev.</hi> 3. Upon ſuch Terms are Juſtification, Adoption, Salvation offered, and not Offered but upon Terms, and yet moſt Freely and Graciouſly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. Freely by his Grace, and yet through Faith, no otherwiſe but upon ſuch Terms, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 18. Upon the ſame Terms we are Adopted, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. We are ſaved by Grace, but through Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. And not only Faith, but Holineſs of Heart and Life, and Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance therein, are the Terms upon which Salvation is Promiſed, <hi>Mat. 5. Heb. 12. 14. Rev. 2. 10. Mark</hi> 13. 13. It is all one as if they were expreſſed Conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60922:76"/> This is not becauſe the Lord makes a Conditional Bargain with us, leaving the Condition to our own Wills, being uncertain whether it will be made good or no: But the reaſon is, becauſe Divine Wiſdom has made a Connexion betwixt theſe Bleſſings, ſo that they ſhall never be ſeparated; one of them ſhall not be had without the other: No Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication without Faith, no Salvation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Holineſs, no Glory without Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: And has Conſtituted an Order amongſt them, ſo that one of them muſt go before the other: We muſt Believe before we be Juſtified, and be Holy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can ſee God. And has appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of them to be the Means or way to obtain the other: We are Juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied by Faith, we are Created unto good Works, that we ſhould walk in them. Acts of Holy Obedience are the way wherein we muſt walk to Salvation: So that here is an Antecedence of ſome Duty, and that neceſſary by Divine Appointment and Command, and this tending to obtain a Favour freely offered.</p>
               <p>And by this we may underſtand what a Condition is, in a ſenſe very innocent, and no way injurious to Grace. It is an
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60922:77"/> Antecedent neceſſarily required, as the way to attain or arrive at what is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
               <p>And in this Senſe it muſt not be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that there are Conditions in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and its Promiſes; unleſs we will deny that there are Duties neceſſary to Salvation, and made neceſſary by Divine Command: For ſuch a Condition is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſomething of a Command joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Promiſe in a conditional Form; and Divine Commands muſt be no more queſtioned, when they are joyned with Promiſes, than when they are delivered apart. He Commands all to Repent, and he promiſes Pardon: Put this Promiſe and that Command together, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Conditional Promiſe; if you Repent, you ſhall have Pardon, or as the Apoſtle delivers it, 1 <hi>Joh. 1. 9. If we Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our Sins, he is faithful and juſt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our Sins, and to cleanſe us from all our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) There are Conditions that <hi>are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to Grace,</hi> and <hi>Inconſiſtent</hi> with it: None ſuch are annexed to any Promiſe of the Goſpel, none ſuch muſt be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thoſe who will reſerve to the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60922:77"/> Lord the Honour of his Grace, or have our Salvation intirely aſcribed to it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Meritorious Conditions,</hi> when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is preſumed to deſerve what is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: There is no ſuch Condition of Salvation as this, but in the proud Fancies of Preſumptuous Sinners. For, 1. There muſt be a Diſproportion between that which is procured, and the Condition that deſerves it: It is of Favour, not of Merit, if the promiſed Bleſſing exceed the worth of the Condition. To make this plain; ſuppoſe the worth of a days Work be twelve Pence, a Man Promiſes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a thouſand Crowns for a days La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; it cannot in any reaſon be imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that his days Labour deſerves ſo much; if he receive ſo much, he has it of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour not of Merit. Now the Diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is far greater betwixt Salvation, and all that is required of us in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: Sufferings for Chriſt are more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable on this account than holy Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but all the Sufferings of this Life, ſuch as thoſe of the Apoſtle and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, bear not the ſleighteſt Proportion to the Glory Promiſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 18. there is no Proportion betwixt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60922:78"/> them; the Glory offered does infinitely exceed them; it is the Eternal Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God himſelf; and between that which is finite and infinite there is no Proportion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17. If Glory were Promiſed on theſe Terms, as it ſeems to be, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 12. yet Suffering would be far from Deſerving the Crown; there is no correſpondent worth in them to ſo vaſt a Crown. Merit quite excludes Grace; for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is deſerved is due in Juſtice, it is a juſt Debt; but that which is of Debt, is not, cannot be of Grace, if the Apoſtle underſtood theſe things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 4. He makes a plain Oppoſition between Grace and Debt. And therefore, if by the Performance of any Condition we can deſerve Salvation, it will be of Debt, and we muſt expunge the Text, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude we are not ſaved by Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Natural Conditions,</hi> ſuch as may be Performed by the Power of Nature, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the concurrence of Omnipotent or Special Grace. All that is required to Salvation, under the notion of Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, muſt be of this Nature, by that Doctrine which will have nothing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Performance thereof, but
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60922:78"/> Suaſive Grace: For this gives no Power ſufficient for Performance; and therefore if there be any Performance, it muſt be by the Power of Nature. Their Grace gives not the Power, but ſuppoſes it in the Will already: All that it can juſtly pretend to, is to Excite what it ſinds, not what it gives. It does not, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubdue the Wills Corruptions, natural and contracted, which is its Moral Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency: And that which leaves it Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as it found it, gives it not Power; it plants no Principle of Spiritual Life and Strength in the Will, but diſclaims theſe expreſly. And as it does not give the Power, ſo neither does it give the Act; it determins not the Will, nor cauſes it to Act; but leaves it to incline as it liſt, when there is no Principle in it to incline it towards that which is Saving, and Corruption enough to incline it the other way.</p>
               <p>The Caſe ſtanding thus, if the Will comply with the Terms of Salvation, it muſt be by its own Power, ſince it has no more from above: And then, in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Text, Salvation will be of our ſelves, by our own Strength, not by Grace; nor will Grace which is Saving,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60922:79"/> be the Gift of God: For if he give nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Power, nor the Act, who can imagine how it can be counted his Gift? They may as well ſay, we are Saved by the Power of Nature, as that the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Salvation are to be Performed by ſuch a Power, without any other Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No <hi>Legal Conditions,</hi> no Conditions performed by us, nor our Righteouſneſs. The Righteouſneſs by which we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the Righteouſneſs by which we have Pardon, or by which we have Right and Title to Salvation. Neither Faith, nor ſincere Obedience, are required of us for this end; nor can they, when Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us, be any ſuch Righteouſneſs. It is Chriſt, and he alone, that is our Righteouſneſs; it is by his Righteouſneſs, and that alone, that we are Juſtified: It was he, who by his Obedience to Death ſatisfied Divine Juſtice, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured Title to Eternal Life. It is not pretended that any Performances of ours do or can ſatisfie Divine Juſtice; nor can it with more reaſon be pretended, that our Performances give us Title to Life. Thoſe that ſay he did not both, may as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60922:79"/> well ſay he did neither. Our Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances may evidence our Title, but they give it not, nor are the Ground of it. It is Chriſt, his Righteouſneſs, that is the only Foundation of our Title, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 4. The <hi>End of the Law,</hi> i. e. of the Covenant of Works, was, that Man, by the Righteouſneſs of Perfect Obedience, might have Title to Eternal Life; this being rendered Impoſſible in Mans fallen and ſinful State, how ſhall the End of the Law, which the Lord aimed at, be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? Why, Chriſt attains the End of the Law by his Righteouſneſs, giving Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to Life to thoſe who believe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> are not our Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; now, as Perfect Obedience was to be in the State of Innocency, they are not in the ſtead of it, they have not the Vertue and Office of it, they are not Conditions of the Covenant of Grace, as that was of the Covenant of Works; <hi>i. e.</hi> They are not the Righteouſneſs by which we are Juſtified, and have Title to Life: It is <hi>Chriſt</hi> that <hi>is the End of the Law for Righteouſneſs</hi> to thoſe Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and to aſcribe that to our Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which is proper to him, is injurious to the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:60922:80"/>
               <p>And how is it of Grace upon theſe Terms? how is the Covenant of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel more Gracious than that of Works? It cannot be ſaid that it is more Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, becauſe it requires and accepts leſs, ſincere Obedience being not ſo much as that which is Perfect: For ſincere Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may be counted as much to Man in his preſent State of Sin and Impotency, as Perfect Obedience in the State of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and Perfection. But the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Graciouſneſs of the Goſpel Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, conſiſts not in requiring leſs Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to give Title to Life, than was due at firſt; but in not requiring a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Righteouſneſs of us Perſonally for that end, but providing and accepting that of a ſurety, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3, 4. The Law could not give us Life, becauſe being weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſin, we could not Perform the Perfect Righteouſneſs which is required; but what the Law could not do, Chriſt has done, giving us Title to Life, fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Righteouſneſs of it in our behalf. But does not the Scripture declare, that our Obedience is the Obedience which gives Title to Life? <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 14. I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, There is a double Right, <hi>Jus: ad
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60922:80"/> rem,</hi> and <hi>Jus in re;</hi> a Right of Title, and a Right of Poſſeſſion: Holy Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence gives us not the Title, but leads us into Poſſeſſion. It gives not the Title, for that we have in Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18. Now Obedience is after Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo cannot give that which is before it ſelf, and does not give that which is given already. But it leads us into Poſſeſſion, it is the Way by which we enter; ſo the Word immediately ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing will have it underſtood. When the Apoſtle had declared that we are Saved by Grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 8. and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Works, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. that we may count this to be our Title to Salvation, yet he adds, <hi>Ver. 10. We are his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, which God hath before ordained that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> Theſe are the Ways wherein we muſt walk, if we will arrive at Salvation; but they are not our Title to it, as Perfect Obedience would have been in the firſt Covenant, the Law of Works; they are not ſuch Conditions, they are not our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (upon which our Title is Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) as that was deſigned to be: They are not Legal Conditions.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:60922:81"/>
               <p>4. <hi>Obliging Conditions.</hi> There is no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of ours, that can of it ſelf oblige the Lord to perform any Promiſe; the reaſon, becauſe it is defective, and falls ſhort of what is required: And amongſt men, he that promiſes upon Conditions is not obliged, if the Terms be not duely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. The Law of our Creation requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us perfect Performance; and no leſs than perfect Obedience to God will be due from us, while we are Creatures. It is true, Man now wants Power to anſwer his Ingagements, but that was through his own fault; and the Lord does not loſe his due, becauſe Man ſins againſt him. Now being defective, and falling ſhort of his Duty, it is ſinfull; and that which is ſinfull, is to be puniſhed, not rewarded, as ſuch it has not a Moral fitneſs for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Reward; that which is ſinfull, brings the performer under the Curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. it deſerves eternal Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. and ſo cannot oblige the Lord to reward it.</p>
               <p>Upon this account, the beſt performance of any ſuppoſed Condition, is ſo far of it ſelf from making any promiſed Bleſſing to be due in point of Juſtice, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make it due in point of Faithfulneſs.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:60922:81"/> That which needs Pardon cannot of it ſelf make any thing due to us, but Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Our Faith, our Repentance, our Obedience, being ſinfully defective, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not as ſuch make any thing due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o us, but Puniſhment; and ſo cannot oblige the Lord to perform the Promiſes, to juſtifie, pardon, or ſave us: For that which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the Lord to execute the Threatning, cannot oblige him to fulfill his Promiſe. How then is the Lord obliged? How come the Promiſes to be accompliſhed? Why, not upon the account of our defective Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, but for Chriſts ſake, and ſo through Grace.</p>
               <p>Chriſt has ſatisfied for the ſins of his People, for the ſinful defects of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances: Upon his account they are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and accepted, and ſo for his ſake they are rewarded, and the Promiſes performed. Thus, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 20. all the Promiſes are performed with unvariable Faithfulneſs; he engages the Faithfulneſs of God to fulfill all the Promiſes, when as our Performances, conſidered in themſelves, do oblige him and would rather engage him againſt it.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertain Conditions.</hi> When it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether the Condition will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60922:82"/> or no. Such Conditions have place amongſt Men, and Men only, ſuch as ſuſpend the Affair <hi>in eventum incertum,</hi> and leave it at uncertainty as to the Event; it is uncertain whether the Condition will be performed or not, and ſo uncertain whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Promiſe will be performed. The Reaſon why Man propoſes ſuch Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is his Weakneſs and Imperfection, for want of Power or Foreſight. He has not the Wills of others in his Power, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make them comply with his Will, and ſo cannot tell what they will do. So that it is alſo for want of certain Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge or Foreſight, when we will not beſtow a Favour on another, but upon Terms. If we were certain that the Terms would be obſerved, we would promiſe Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely; if we were certain the Condition would not be obſerved, we would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe at all; but becauſe we are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, therefore we promiſe Conditionally. Now the Ground of theſe Conditions being Weakneſs, they muſt in no wiſe be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto God. It derogates from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom, and infallible Foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; it derogates from his Power and Providence over mans Will and human Affairs: it derogates from the Efficacy of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:60922:82"/> his Grace, as tho this could not determin mans Will, or prevail with it certainly and infallibly to comply with his Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals; but muſt leave it indifferent, and in ſuſpenſe, and ſo at uncertainty, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will comply or not comply with what he propounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>For <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>(1.) <hi>Acknowledge this Grace?</hi> How? By getting high Apprehenſions of it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining frequent Thoughts about it. Say, <hi>How precious are thy Thoughts to me, O God! how great is the ſumm of them!</hi> Let the Meditation hereof be ſweeter than the Honey and the Honey-combe.</item>
                     <item>(2.) Let this <hi>beget ſuitable Affections,</hi> Love, Joy, Admiration, Delight, both in the Fountain and Streams of Free-Grace.</item>
                     <item>(3.) Let it be <hi>a Motive to all Holineſs and Obedience.</hi> Let the Grace of God, the Love of Chriſt conſtrain you to an Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſneſs to him, and Affectionateneſs to one another. If God ſo loved us, how ought we love one another!</item>
                     <item>(4.) Let it <hi>ſtrengthen our Faith</hi> in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:60922:83"/> and Temptations, from the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Sin and ſenſe of unworthineſs.</item>
                     <item>(5.) <hi>Hold it forth to others:</hi> Take all Occaſions to magnifie it; oppoſe every Practice and Opinion that obſcures the Luſtre of it. Uſe it as a Touch-ſtone, to diſcover what Perſons are moſt holy, what Tenents are moſt true, even thoſe which moſt illuſtrate Free Grace.</item>
                     <item>(6.) By <hi>glorying in the Lord;</hi> uſing it to make us and keep us humble. We had nothing to <hi>merit,</hi> nothing to move, for Salvation: what we are, or have, we are by, and have from this Grace. Let no man <hi>boaſt, Rom.</hi> 9. If you have any laudable, amiable Accompliſhments, give the glory to God.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>For <hi>Motives.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>1. Conſider, <hi>how thankfull Gods ancient People</hi> were for <hi>Temporal Salvation;</hi> what ſweet Strains of gratefull Hearts appear in thoſe Songs of Praiſes which we find Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded uſually after any Deliverance. And have we not much more reaſon to be thankfull for <hi>Eternal Salvation?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:60922:83"/>
                     <item>2. Conſider what a <hi>comprehenſive Bleſſing Salvation is,</hi> and take an Eſtimate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by comparing it with the Temporal Deliverances of the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> Thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a Common ordinary Love, theſe from a Peculiar diſtinguiſhing Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Their Deliverances were effected, not without the Hazard of of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; our Salvation is Effected only by the Blood of Chriſt: The Iſſue of theirs was not much more than Civil Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, ſitting under their Vines and Figg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees; the Iſſue of ours is Grace, Glory, Joy, and thoſe things that Eye has not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor have entred into the Heart of Man to conceive.</item>
                     <item>3. This is <hi>the End of all God does in the World,</hi> even to Glorifie himſelf; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. in ſhowing the <hi>Exceeding Riches of his Grace,</hi> in his Kindneſs towards us through Jeſus Chriſt: Now we have no other way to Glorifie him, but by an active affectionate Acknowledgment of his Grace.</item>
                     <item>4. This is <hi>the Employment of gloryfied Spirits</hi> in Heaven, to Praiſe, Admire and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:60922:84"/> Adore this Grace: This is the Subject of thoſe Seraphick Praiſes. The thoughts of this ſtupendious Love tranſports Angels and Men into an eternal Rapture. This is the way to be in Heaven upon Earth, to anticipate Glory, to enter into our Maſters Joy before we come at it: Nay, this is the way by which our Maſters Joy enters into us. Never are our Souls filled with ſuch Raviſhing Pleaſures, as when we are taken up with ſuch heavenly Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Never do we riſe higher above the World, than when theſe Thoughts wing our Souls: Nay, ſometimes they will <hi>ſteal into Heaven,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Spyes into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and bring from thence into our Souls, Grapes, and Figgs, and Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, ſome taſte of what we ſhall fully enjoy in the Land of Promiſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salvation</hi> is a comprehenſive Bleſſing; it includes the Eternal Love of God; that is its Foundation: Which Eternal Love broke forht in time into ſuch high Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as to ſend his Son, to live miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, and dye ſhamefully for us, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt us in all the Merits of his Death. This was the Purchaſe of Salvation, and it is the Concluſion; as thô unwilling thoſe whom he loves ſo well, ſhould be
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:60922:84"/> at ſuch a diſtance from him, takes us to Himſelf, to ſee his Glory, to Bathe our ſelves in that Stream of Bliſs, in thoſe Rivers of Pleaſure that are at his Right Hand. This is the Accompliſhment of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; ſure this deſerves to be Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:85"/>
            <head>Books written and publiſhed by Mr. <hi>John Howe</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, and ſold by <hi>Tho. Parkhuſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 THe Bleſſedneſs of the Righteous, opened: And further Recommended from the Conſideration of the Vanity of this Mortal Life: In two Treatiſes, on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 15. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 47.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of Thoughtfulneſs for the Morrow. With an Appendix concerning the Immoderate Deſire of fore knowing things to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Redeemers Tears wept over Loſt Souls. A Treatiſe on <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 41, 42. with an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix, wherein ſomewhat is diſcourſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Blasphemy againſt the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and how God is ſaid to <hi>will the Salvation of them that periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Of Charity in reference to other mens Sins.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60922:85"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
